<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-11-11T08:46:51-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Community Trash</title><subtitle>A website for a fae 🧚🏻‍♂️</subtitle><author><name>Missy</name></author><entry><title type="html">Building your community: Community standards and codes of conduct</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/archived/community-standards-and-coc" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building your community: Community standards and codes of conduct" /><published>2023-08-28T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-08-28T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/archived/community%20standards%20and%20coc</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/archived/community-standards-and-coc"><![CDATA[<details>
<summary><b>AUTHOR NOTE</b></summary>
<i>This was originally posted on my WordPress blog, which I have deleted after migrating the blog's posts to this website in November 2025. Differences from the original are minimal and include: adding paragraphs to reduce the wall of text, adding in a break from the series intro, grammatical adjustments throughout the post, adjusting text formatting a little, and linking properly to my Bluesky account.</i>
</details>
<p><br /></p>
<h3 id="building-your-community">building your community</h3>
<p>Alright, this post was <em>not</em> supposed to be the second one of this series, but I am pushing it up after <a href="https://news.yahoo.com/bluesky-allowed-people-to-include-the-n-word-in-their-usernames-184049864.html">a really dumb situation happened on Bluesky</a> about two weeks after I gained access to the platform; one that could have easily been prevented had there been solid and inclusive community standards or code of conduct (because if they cared about these things the situation would have been caught early). If you missed the first post in this series, <a href="/archived/start-building-your-community">get started building your community</a> before diving into this post. I’ll leave my thoughts on the whole Bluesky situation on other platforms (<em>unless you already follow me on <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/adorablecyb.org">Bluesky</a></em>) to keep the focus on the content of this series. In this post, let me talk to you about community standards and codes of conduct, and how they fold into the activity and health of your community.<br />
<br /></p>
<hr />
<p><br />
What’s the difference between community standards and a code of conduct? Honestly, I’ve found that they can be interchangeable phrases in the industry. Both seem to stem from the legal aspects of running a business - <b>community standards</b> being around how community members are expected to behave, and a <b>code of conduct</b> being more of the legal side of things related to ethics, but both should have consequences tied to them when it comes to your community space. I tend to call them Community Guidelines myself, but you should choose the term that your company leans on.<br />
<br />
The best example of guidelines I found recently is the set <a href="https://docs.replit.com/legal-and-security-info/trust-and-safety">Replit</a> has. It clearly states the expectations of the community and how to treat each other, how they should handle their personal information on a public space, and are <a href="https://docs.replit.com/legal-and-security-info/strike-system-faq">explicit in the consequences</a> for not following them. While consequences hardly need to be public, if you are a product or company who prides itself with open communication and transparency, you should have them available to your community to align with your values.<br />
<br />
While I believe that <em>all</em> communities have standards, not every one does. Most have generic ones to cover the legal bases of discrimination, really do not care what happens to community members, and allows them to moderate themselves. In recent years, the latter has proved to fuel bad actors by allowing abusive behavior towards marginalized groups. <b>Community standards are <em>a must</em></b> as a company or product running social spaces, imho. This not only ensures a safe community for the users but <em>the employees</em>, too! You can’t hold <em>anyone</em> accountable for their actions in your community if you have no guidelines - there’s nothing to reference when you say that a person is not behaving in a way that is tolerated within your community.<br />
<br />
Places like Reddit and Discord have enough terms of use that companies can fall back on for illegal activities in which they can use to remove bad actors to avoid more harm. This helps in a couple different ways: there’s a trust and safety team dedicated to the high level protection of their users, and they offer tools to allow community moderators and leaders to curate standards for their own spaces (AutoMod and moderator bots, for example). These are your best case scenarios when using a social platform because you can escalate to Reddit or Discord employees if you need to but also customize guidelines to your own community.<br />
<br />
Something I find open-source or developer-focused companies are starting to eyeball is <a href="https://nocodeofconduct.com">No Code of Conduct</a>. <em><b>Avoid this</b></em>. While a lot of cishet white tech bros think that everyone can have conversations without treating each other like assholes (see: Xitter), the reality is that <b>people rarely think on how their words impact others</b>. If you want a community that flourishes outside of your product, having community guidelines will ensure all members feel safe and heard - especially if you follow consistent moderation practices and have trusted members as moderators <em>(a topic for a future blog</em>). Users who see they have no consequences will abuse a situation and quickly become bad actors in your community.<br />
<br />
Okay, I’ve given an example of what looks great and what you probably should avoid when it comes to how your guidelines should be set up. How does this all roll into and affect the activity and health of your community? Well, <b>healthy community standards</b> often end up building <b>strong communities that self-moderate</b>. This should be an end goal for your community - yes, <em>you SHOULD work your way out of a job</em>, that’s how you know you were successful! Having these built up will give your community moderators who volunteer their time something to point to when they are attempting to keep peace.<br />
<br />
But wait! It also gives those who <em>are not</em> volunteer mods something to point to if they feel the guidelines have been broken! This empowers <em>everyone</em> in your community to encourage psychological safety following the guidance from the company representatives. Having a way to escalate up to either the social platform or a company rep who maintains communities will give the community another path to ensure guidelines are followed; <em>especially</em> if it seems like a moderator has gone off the rails, it will give your regular members a safe avenue to report it. All of this will lead to the community members trusting that your community spaces are there for you to listen to their feedback, and where they can find others who enjoy your stuff, too.<br />
<br />
Whenever I step into new community spaces, I <b>evaluate what guidelines are already in place</b> and look to adjust things as needed. The important thing here is to <b>include the moderators</b> who are already in place - they are often experts of the community and can help make adjustments that they think should happen. If you <b>come in swinging</b> with new standards and didn’t bother telling the volunteer moderators who have been doing it before you, you’re going to have a hard time earning their trust which can <b>seed distrust in the community</b> overall.<br />
<br />
And if you get stuck trying to figure out what should be adjusted for your community, you can <em>always</em> ask the whole community to chime in! People love when employees include them in decisions when it comes to their community spaces. Need more help? You can find me on <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/adorablecyb.org">Bluesky</a> for now - I am more than happy to chat with you and offer advice on your guidelines. Now that you know where to start building your community and how to build up expectations for them, next up in this series is building a new server in Discord, a subreddit on Reddit, or creating your own forum!<br />
<br />
<b>A community should be a communal effort</b> - if it’s not, isn’t it just authortarian at that point?<br />
<br />
-🧜🏻‍♀️🦄</p>]]></content><author><name>the cyborg</name></author><category term="archived" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[AUTHOR NOTE This was originally posted on my WordPress blog, which I have deleted after migrating the blog's posts to this website in November 2025. Differences from the original are minimal and include: adding paragraphs to reduce the wall of text, adding in a break from the series intro, grammatical adjustments throughout the post, adjusting text formatting a little, and linking properly to my Bluesky account. building your community Alright, this post was not supposed to be the second one of this series, but I am pushing it up after a really dumb situation happened on Bluesky about two weeks after I gained access to the platform; one that could have easily been prevented had there been solid and inclusive community standards or code of conduct (because if they cared about these things the situation would have been caught early). If you missed the first post in this series, get started building your community before diving into this post. I’ll leave my thoughts on the whole Bluesky situation on other platforms (unless you already follow me on Bluesky) to keep the focus on the content of this series. In this post, let me talk to you about community standards and codes of conduct, and how they fold into the activity and health of your community. What’s the difference between community standards and a code of conduct? Honestly, I’ve found that they can be interchangeable phrases in the industry. Both seem to stem from the legal aspects of running a business - community standards being around how community members are expected to behave, and a code of conduct being more of the legal side of things related to ethics, but both should have consequences tied to them when it comes to your community space. I tend to call them Community Guidelines myself, but you should choose the term that your company leans on. The best example of guidelines I found recently is the set Replit has. It clearly states the expectations of the community and how to treat each other, how they should handle their personal information on a public space, and are explicit in the consequences for not following them. While consequences hardly need to be public, if you are a product or company who prides itself with open communication and transparency, you should have them available to your community to align with your values. While I believe that all communities have standards, not every one does. Most have generic ones to cover the legal bases of discrimination, really do not care what happens to community members, and allows them to moderate themselves. In recent years, the latter has proved to fuel bad actors by allowing abusive behavior towards marginalized groups. Community standards are a must as a company or product running social spaces, imho. This not only ensures a safe community for the users but the employees, too! You can’t hold anyone accountable for their actions in your community if you have no guidelines - there’s nothing to reference when you say that a person is not behaving in a way that is tolerated within your community. Places like Reddit and Discord have enough terms of use that companies can fall back on for illegal activities in which they can use to remove bad actors to avoid more harm. This helps in a couple different ways: there’s a trust and safety team dedicated to the high level protection of their users, and they offer tools to allow community moderators and leaders to curate standards for their own spaces (AutoMod and moderator bots, for example). These are your best case scenarios when using a social platform because you can escalate to Reddit or Discord employees if you need to but also customize guidelines to your own community. Something I find open-source or developer-focused companies are starting to eyeball is No Code of Conduct. Avoid this. While a lot of cishet white tech bros think that everyone can have conversations without treating each other like assholes (see: Xitter), the reality is that people rarely think on how their words impact others. If you want a community that flourishes outside of your product, having community guidelines will ensure all members feel safe and heard - especially if you follow consistent moderation practices and have trusted members as moderators (a topic for a future blog). Users who see they have no consequences will abuse a situation and quickly become bad actors in your community. Okay, I’ve given an example of what looks great and what you probably should avoid when it comes to how your guidelines should be set up. How does this all roll into and affect the activity and health of your community? Well, healthy community standards often end up building strong communities that self-moderate. This should be an end goal for your community - yes, you SHOULD work your way out of a job, that’s how you know you were successful! Having these built up will give your community moderators who volunteer their time something to point to when they are attempting to keep peace. But wait! It also gives those who are not volunteer mods something to point to if they feel the guidelines have been broken! This empowers everyone in your community to encourage psychological safety following the guidance from the company representatives. Having a way to escalate up to either the social platform or a company rep who maintains communities will give the community another path to ensure guidelines are followed; especially if it seems like a moderator has gone off the rails, it will give your regular members a safe avenue to report it. All of this will lead to the community members trusting that your community spaces are there for you to listen to their feedback, and where they can find others who enjoy your stuff, too. Whenever I step into new community spaces, I evaluate what guidelines are already in place and look to adjust things as needed. The important thing here is to include the moderators who are already in place - they are often experts of the community and can help make adjustments that they think should happen. If you come in swinging with new standards and didn’t bother telling the volunteer moderators who have been doing it before you, you’re going to have a hard time earning their trust which can seed distrust in the community overall. And if you get stuck trying to figure out what should be adjusted for your community, you can always ask the whole community to chime in! People love when employees include them in decisions when it comes to their community spaces. Need more help? You can find me on Bluesky for now - I am more than happy to chat with you and offer advice on your guidelines. Now that you know where to start building your community and how to build up expectations for them, next up in this series is building a new server in Discord, a subreddit on Reddit, or creating your own forum! A community should be a communal effort - if it’s not, isn’t it just authortarian at that point? -🧜🏻‍♀️🦄]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The art of social listening</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/archived/art-of-social-listening" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The art of social listening" /><published>2023-07-11T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-07-11T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/archived/art%20of%20social%20listening</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/archived/art-of-social-listening"><![CDATA[<details>
<summary><b>AUTHOR NOTE</b></summary>
<i>This was originally posted on my WordPress blog, which I have deleted after migrating the blog's posts to this website in November 2025. Differences from the original are minimal and include: adding paragraphs to reduce the wall of text, rephrasing a few sentences to make more sense, adjusting text formatting, changing Twitter to Xitter because fuck Elon Musk, and adding an Author's Note about Orbit.love.</i>
</details>
<p><br />
Something that’s been on my mind lately is just how many companies are looking for a technical person to help them talk to their users on social media to pull insights out of their feedback. People who can do that really well, like me, aren’t common, which made me realize that maybe not a lot of people truly understand the art of social listening in product management. Today I want to talk about how I do social listening; consider this a kind of sequel post to <a href="/archived/art-of-empathy">The art of empathy</a> or maybe a follow up to <a href="/archived/translating-user-feedback">how I translate feedback from users</a>. 😁<br />
<br />
What do I mean when I say <b>social listening</b>? Social listening is known as the process of <b>monitoring what people say</b> about you, your competitors, and other keywords you want to include <b>on social media platforms</b>. It’s an organic source of feedback that typically offers candid insights from your and your competitor’s users, often putting you at an advantage. I’m a special type of human who can glean insights from social listening both manually and with tooling, and excellent at convincing colleagues to listen to and act on the data I bring them.<br />
<br />
<b>Knowing your audience</b> is key. You’ll see me harping on that a lot, and I don’t mean <em>knowing your audience</em> in the marketing sense - it’s all about how they <em>communicate</em> with each other. I stressed in <a href="/archived/translating-user-feedback">a previous blog</a> that <b>understanding how your users speak to each other</b> is probably the <em>most important thing</em> you can learn in order to translate their feedback. I ended it by saying <b>building relationships with your colleagues</b> who will champion for you internally is key to successfully translate feedback.<br />
<br />
<em><b>Both of these are true for social listening</b></em>.<br />
<br />
If you are in a community management or marketing role, you <em>must</em> have good relationships with your product and engineering colleagues for them to trust the social listening insights you bring to them. If you are a product manager doing social listening as a part of your role being customer obsessed, you’ll need the skill of translating feedback to effectively articulate the data behind your users’ voices. I cannot stress enough the importance of <b>understanding what people are saying</b> before you can <b>extrapolate their meanings</b>.<br />
<br />
Now, you will find that there is a huge difference between <b>how people speak <em>about</em> you</b> and <b>how they speak <em>to</em> you</b>. Community members will say one thing in a private survey while simultaneously ranting on <em>~social platform~</em> about the opposing opinion. My style of <b>social listening includes following up with users</b> - this is where I found empathy is the most valuable skill. If you get clearance from legal/privacy teams to ask for contact information in a survey, or have a CMS that already provides that data, emailing users back based on their survey results can often improve brand perspective. The same can be said for social media.<br />
<br />
Several <b>in-app feedback tools</b> support <b>responding to people</b> who provide their email address, which is an amazing way to gather more information about what they sent and acts as an email communication. I trained the Microsoft Edge team on how to <b>talk to people with empathy</b> and follow privacy policies; the legal team can make things boring sometimes, but I also understand the need to protect a company from liability, <em>I guess</em>. 🙄 Trying to find out more about <b>what the person is saying</b>, through either public or private communications, goes a long way to <b>earn their trust</b> and helps you make informed decisions based on community feedback.<br />
<br />
The cherry on top for users is when <b>you come back to them</b> and <b>thank them</b> for the in depth conversation, then let them know what happened with their suggestion; either it was placed in the product, or maybe you are letting them know that the change won’t be implemented. When I brought bad news to community members, they reacted kindly with an understanding that not everything can make it into a product and respected the fact that I went to lengths to <b>make sure they were heard</b>.<br />
<br />
You will need something to effectively <b>track what your users are saying</b>. There are a variety of tools out there that can help most products do this, but I <em>do not</em> suggest anyone does social listening tracking like I was forced to. It was painfully manual and I <b>couldn’t scale</b>. I used Sprinklr, like everyone else at Microsoft, but I had the “privilege” of owning listening for a product named after <em>a common English word</em>. This meant that <b>removing noise</b> from social data was <em>significantly</em> difficult without a ton of query-tuning and metadata tagging. Even worse, Sprinklr does <em>not</em> work well with <b>contextual sentiment</b>. Weekly I manually adjusted the sentiment labeling in Sprinklr for my owned handle. Thank the <em>gods</em> I had very little mentions comparatively because, until I knew my community and the browser well enough, <b>that process took forever</b> to do.<br />
<br />
I only did this for Twitter because Reddit tracking in Sprinklr was <em>worse</em> than its ability to contextualize sentiment; at least in my past experiences. Now that both Reddit and Xitter have restricted their APIs, I am curious to know how much it’s impacted Sprinklr’s functionality… or subscription fees… 🤔<br />
<br />
Since Reddit was one of my top focuses on the team, I tracked posts utilizing Microsft Edge’s Collections feature. Daily I created a collection of the new posts in the subreddit to export the post metadata into an Excel spreadsheet that I then copied to put into <em>another</em> spreadsheet for the team’s tracking, assigning sentiment manually for these posts. Because the Edge Insider Tech Community forum was a product <em>group space</em> owned by another team, I could get data for activity but didn’t have a system that would organize the posts in a way to answer them. Instead of fighting that, I said screw it and utilized Excel for tracking forum posts.<br />
<br />
Yes, <em><b>I really fucking did this</b></em>. I pushed <em>incredibly</em> hard to get off of this process with very little success. So, <em>please</em> don’t be like me and manually adjust sentiment while also manually logging social posts from your subreddits and forums in an Excel spreadsheet. 😭<br />
<br />
Instead, if you can get around the shortcomings of Sprinklr, it’s not a <em>terrible</em> tool. It works well for a lot of the things that I did not use it for, and its reporting is quite good - I had several teammates around the world who were a part of my team in Sprinklr and could pull custom reports based on what spaces I listened to all up, which reduced the need for me to do this after I helped them get set up.<br />
<br />
The explosion of AI since I started this blog has very likely shifted how social listening products out there are working, however there are a few tools that I suggest digging into if Sprinklr isn’t quite what you are looking for. Orbit.love is an amazing open-source product that helps you see your community’s “orbit”. I love the play on words for this, mostly because I’m a space nerd, and would <em>love</em> to use this product in whatever my next role is. With the ability to monitor several social platforms outside of traditional social media, and the ability for you to add in other spaces by contributing to the project, it gives you a very large picture of where your biggest fans are and where you need to nurture your community.<br />
<br /></p>
<details>
<summary><b>AUTHOR'S NOTE, Nov 2025</b></summary>
<i>orbit.love no longer seems to exist, which is pretty sad. It was <a href="https://blog.postman.com/announcing-postman-has-acquired-orbit/">acquired by Postman</a> in April 2024, shortly after I started working for Nabu Casa, but now listed as part of <a href="https://jetrockets.com/portfolio/orbitlove">JetRockets' portfolio</a>. From what I can tell, this is just another open source victim of being gobbled up by the tech industry.</i> 😔
</details>
<p><br />
<a href="https://www.hootsuite.com">Hootsuite</a> is a very common tool used across the industry that has a lot of solid social listening features. It can help you <b>track the performance of your content</b> compared to your competitors, a very valuable insight in what kind of content works in your world of the tech industry. The last tool I like for social listening, and what my content team for Edge used, is <a href="https://brand24.com/">Brand24</a>. I have found that it does contextual sentiment a little better than Sprinklr does and the reporting is super detailed but easy to read. The ability to <b>easily dig into insights</b> with Brand24 is also quite nice, imo.<br />
<br />
But wait, <em>what do you do with all of this information</em>? If you’re a community lead of some sort, you can <b>start building up your social listening strategy</b> now! Building one for social listening is just like any other feature that a product or program manager may own. First, <b>find your goals</b> when it comes to social listening in your role. This is different for each role. Mine were around CSAT, but I also tracked NPS and sentiment. If you are a feature owner, you may have different goals like sentiment or adoption/usage of your feature.<br />
<br />
Next, <b>find the tool that best suits <em>your</em> needs</b>. I named only four out of the <em>dozens</em> of tools out there based on my own experience with them but there are many others that may work better for you! Once you know the capabilities of the tool you choose, <b>figure out what terms to track</b>! It’s really good practice to listen for your company and product name, your competitors, any public figures that work at your company, and keywords directly related to your industry. A little bit of fine-tuning listening queries then should now be <b>set up for success to start social listening</b> for your and your competitors’ users and <b>start acting on those insights</b> you find!<br />
<br />
Now, I’m off to <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/missyquarry_this-whole-seven-twitters-situation-is-quite-activity-7084266577960857600-g7KG/">continue my people-watching</a> as we all shift from one social platform to the next, something that will very likely <em>outdate this entire post soon</em>. 😂<br />
<br />
-🧜🏻‍♀️🦄</p>]]></content><author><name>the cyborg</name></author><category term="archived" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[AUTHOR NOTE This was originally posted on my WordPress blog, which I have deleted after migrating the blog's posts to this website in November 2025. Differences from the original are minimal and include: adding paragraphs to reduce the wall of text, rephrasing a few sentences to make more sense, adjusting text formatting, changing Twitter to Xitter because fuck Elon Musk, and adding an Author's Note about Orbit.love. Something that’s been on my mind lately is just how many companies are looking for a technical person to help them talk to their users on social media to pull insights out of their feedback. People who can do that really well, like me, aren’t common, which made me realize that maybe not a lot of people truly understand the art of social listening in product management. Today I want to talk about how I do social listening; consider this a kind of sequel post to The art of empathy or maybe a follow up to how I translate feedback from users. 😁 What do I mean when I say social listening? Social listening is known as the process of monitoring what people say about you, your competitors, and other keywords you want to include on social media platforms. It’s an organic source of feedback that typically offers candid insights from your and your competitor’s users, often putting you at an advantage. I’m a special type of human who can glean insights from social listening both manually and with tooling, and excellent at convincing colleagues to listen to and act on the data I bring them. Knowing your audience is key. You’ll see me harping on that a lot, and I don’t mean knowing your audience in the marketing sense - it’s all about how they communicate with each other. I stressed in a previous blog that understanding how your users speak to each other is probably the most important thing you can learn in order to translate their feedback. I ended it by saying building relationships with your colleagues who will champion for you internally is key to successfully translate feedback. Both of these are true for social listening. If you are in a community management or marketing role, you must have good relationships with your product and engineering colleagues for them to trust the social listening insights you bring to them. If you are a product manager doing social listening as a part of your role being customer obsessed, you’ll need the skill of translating feedback to effectively articulate the data behind your users’ voices. I cannot stress enough the importance of understanding what people are saying before you can extrapolate their meanings. Now, you will find that there is a huge difference between how people speak about you and how they speak to you. Community members will say one thing in a private survey while simultaneously ranting on ~social platform~ about the opposing opinion. My style of social listening includes following up with users - this is where I found empathy is the most valuable skill. If you get clearance from legal/privacy teams to ask for contact information in a survey, or have a CMS that already provides that data, emailing users back based on their survey results can often improve brand perspective. The same can be said for social media. Several in-app feedback tools support responding to people who provide their email address, which is an amazing way to gather more information about what they sent and acts as an email communication. I trained the Microsoft Edge team on how to talk to people with empathy and follow privacy policies; the legal team can make things boring sometimes, but I also understand the need to protect a company from liability, I guess. 🙄 Trying to find out more about what the person is saying, through either public or private communications, goes a long way to earn their trust and helps you make informed decisions based on community feedback. The cherry on top for users is when you come back to them and thank them for the in depth conversation, then let them know what happened with their suggestion; either it was placed in the product, or maybe you are letting them know that the change won’t be implemented. When I brought bad news to community members, they reacted kindly with an understanding that not everything can make it into a product and respected the fact that I went to lengths to make sure they were heard. You will need something to effectively track what your users are saying. There are a variety of tools out there that can help most products do this, but I do not suggest anyone does social listening tracking like I was forced to. It was painfully manual and I couldn’t scale. I used Sprinklr, like everyone else at Microsoft, but I had the “privilege” of owning listening for a product named after a common English word. This meant that removing noise from social data was significantly difficult without a ton of query-tuning and metadata tagging. Even worse, Sprinklr does not work well with contextual sentiment. Weekly I manually adjusted the sentiment labeling in Sprinklr for my owned handle. Thank the gods I had very little mentions comparatively because, until I knew my community and the browser well enough, that process took forever to do. I only did this for Twitter because Reddit tracking in Sprinklr was worse than its ability to contextualize sentiment; at least in my past experiences. Now that both Reddit and Xitter have restricted their APIs, I am curious to know how much it’s impacted Sprinklr’s functionality… or subscription fees… 🤔 Since Reddit was one of my top focuses on the team, I tracked posts utilizing Microsft Edge’s Collections feature. Daily I created a collection of the new posts in the subreddit to export the post metadata into an Excel spreadsheet that I then copied to put into another spreadsheet for the team’s tracking, assigning sentiment manually for these posts. Because the Edge Insider Tech Community forum was a product group space owned by another team, I could get data for activity but didn’t have a system that would organize the posts in a way to answer them. Instead of fighting that, I said screw it and utilized Excel for tracking forum posts. Yes, I really fucking did this. I pushed incredibly hard to get off of this process with very little success. So, please don’t be like me and manually adjust sentiment while also manually logging social posts from your subreddits and forums in an Excel spreadsheet. 😭 Instead, if you can get around the shortcomings of Sprinklr, it’s not a terrible tool. It works well for a lot of the things that I did not use it for, and its reporting is quite good - I had several teammates around the world who were a part of my team in Sprinklr and could pull custom reports based on what spaces I listened to all up, which reduced the need for me to do this after I helped them get set up. The explosion of AI since I started this blog has very likely shifted how social listening products out there are working, however there are a few tools that I suggest digging into if Sprinklr isn’t quite what you are looking for. Orbit.love is an amazing open-source product that helps you see your community’s “orbit”. I love the play on words for this, mostly because I’m a space nerd, and would love to use this product in whatever my next role is. With the ability to monitor several social platforms outside of traditional social media, and the ability for you to add in other spaces by contributing to the project, it gives you a very large picture of where your biggest fans are and where you need to nurture your community. AUTHOR'S NOTE, Nov 2025 orbit.love no longer seems to exist, which is pretty sad. It was acquired by Postman in April 2024, shortly after I started working for Nabu Casa, but now listed as part of JetRockets' portfolio. From what I can tell, this is just another open source victim of being gobbled up by the tech industry. 😔 Hootsuite is a very common tool used across the industry that has a lot of solid social listening features. It can help you track the performance of your content compared to your competitors, a very valuable insight in what kind of content works in your world of the tech industry. The last tool I like for social listening, and what my content team for Edge used, is Brand24. I have found that it does contextual sentiment a little better than Sprinklr does and the reporting is super detailed but easy to read. The ability to easily dig into insights with Brand24 is also quite nice, imo. But wait, what do you do with all of this information? If you’re a community lead of some sort, you can start building up your social listening strategy now! Building one for social listening is just like any other feature that a product or program manager may own. First, find your goals when it comes to social listening in your role. This is different for each role. Mine were around CSAT, but I also tracked NPS and sentiment. If you are a feature owner, you may have different goals like sentiment or adoption/usage of your feature. Next, find the tool that best suits your needs. I named only four out of the dozens of tools out there based on my own experience with them but there are many others that may work better for you! Once you know the capabilities of the tool you choose, figure out what terms to track! It’s really good practice to listen for your company and product name, your competitors, any public figures that work at your company, and keywords directly related to your industry. A little bit of fine-tuning listening queries then should now be set up for success to start social listening for your and your competitors’ users and start acting on those insights you find! Now, I’m off to continue my people-watching as we all shift from one social platform to the next, something that will very likely outdate this entire post soon. 😂 -🧜🏻‍♀️🦄]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Building your community: So you want to start building your community</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/archived/start-building-your-community" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building your community: So you want to start building your community" /><published>2023-06-30T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-06-30T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/archived/start%20building%20your%20community</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/archived/start-building-your-community"><![CDATA[<details>
<summary><b>AUTHOR NOTE</b></summary>
<i>This was originally posted on my WordPress blog, which I have deleted after migrating the blog's posts to this website in November 2025. Differences from the original are minimal and include: grammatical improvements throughout the post, text formatting changes, adding in more paragraphs to reduce the wall of text, and rephrasing the pros and cons bullets to fit better in the HTML table.</i>
</details>
<p><br /></p>
<h3 id="building-your-community">building your community</h3>
<p>A new blog series of mine dedicated to sharing out knowledge on building communities - both from <b>0 &gt; 1</b> and stepping into <b>an established community</b>. I plan to include posts about <em>setting up a new social space</em>, <em>community standards</em>, and <em>moderating</em> in the near future; today I’d like to talk about <b>how to start building communities</b> in the first place. The hardest part is knowing where to start - understanding the benefits and downsides of existing communities versus building a brand new space can help.
<br />
<br /></p>
<hr />
<p><br />
During my time at Microsoft, I became <em>the</em> expert in building and bonding with online communities. I don’t really know exactly how it happened but I befriended people who did the same kind of work I did but for Intune, and I became quite friendly with the Windows Insiders team really early in my role - that’s likely <em>directly</em> related to my notariety as a community expert. I also had great connections on the Xbox Insiders team from my time on Xbox, including one who mentored me on their community building practices for Reddit.<br />
<br />
I stood up the Edge product group connection forums to build relationships with the volunteer moderators and independent advisors for Microsoft’s Answers site as the first product group to pilot the effort. This led me to meeting up with the supportability team back over on Xbox and advising them of how to go through creating their own product space on Answers to build relationships with the same group of volunteers.<br />
<br />
Before I exited Microsoft, I had advised the .NET team on how to stand up a preview community program. On the Xbox Ambassador team, I helped launch and admin their community Discord server in 2017, and I’ve owned/moderated a few different servers over the years since then. Unofficially, I helped out in two community servers dedicated to Microsoft in both consumer and enterprise spaces for the Edge team, with one server honoring me with a Community Hero role (mostly because of my shitposting skills 😂).<br />
<br />
My point is, I’ve been around the community world in a variety of role levels and in this post I want to share some of the pros &amp; cons of stepping into an existing community space as a company representative and standing up an entirely new space for your community to congregate.<br />
<br />
<b>Note</b>: I <em>will not</em> be giving advice on how to market these spaces - it’s my honest opinion that word of mouth will help these spaces organically grow with you engaging genuinely and honoring your word as a company - or admitting when you are wrong and being honest about product changes. 🫰🏻<br />
<br />
There are two different ways one should build or grow a community: either there is an existing community and you want to establish yourself as a company representative to build brand loyalty, or you are going to build up a new space to nurture a baby community from the ground up. There are pros and cons to both of these, but if you think your product doesn’t have an existing community you may be underestimating your users already - I have found communities pre-formed for unlikely products.<br />
<br /></p>
<table class="enhanced-table">
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Existing communities</th>
      <th>New communities</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><b><i>Pros</i></b><br />
        ~ People are already passionate about the product or company<br />
        ~ Spaces likely have moderators who are trusted<br />
        ~ Lots of candid feedback from the past can be dove into
      </td>
      <td><b><i>Pros</i></b><br />
        ~ Unifies the community with the company<br />
        ~ Direct control over admin and moderation tools for metric tracking<br />
        ~ Can identify community leaders before promoting them
      </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><b><i>Cons</i></b><br />
        ~ A lot of tech communities don't trust company representatives<br />
        ~ Moderators or long-time members can have chips on their shoulders<br />
        ~ Limited access to administrative or moderating tools to the space
      </td>
      <td><b><i>Cons</i></b><br />
        ~ Engineering resources are needed to stand up custom platforms<br />
        ~ It takes time to earn trust, candid feedback can be harder to gather<br />
        ~ Need a lot of collaboration across the company to feel authentic<br />
      </td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<style>
.enhanced-table {
  table-layout: fixed;
  width: 95%;
  border-collapse: collapse;
  margin: 10px auto;
  border-top: .5px solid #999;
  border-bottom: .5px solid #999;
  border-left: .5px solid #999;
  border-right: .5px solid #999;
}

.enhanced-table td {
  padding: 12px;
  text-align: left;
}

.enhanced-table th {
  border-bottom: .5px solid #999;
  padding: 10px;
  text-align: left;
  font-weight: bold;
}
</style>

<p><br />
Even though every role I’ve held so far was me stepping into an existing community, this doesn’t mean that I didn’t look to start new community spaces from scratch. One of the worst things about the Microsoft Edge community was that it was so splintered. We didn’t have one centered place where everyone could connect with the team, and we didn’t really have a way to track our biggest fans across all of the spaces we did have. I worked up a few plans to utilize things like Orbit.love to track conversations or repurpose some of our other spaces to organize the community better, but couldn’t earn dev time to help build the tools needed.<br />
<br />
Let’s look further back then. When I worked on the Xbox Support Forums, we spent a long time building an in-house forums customized for the Xbox community because we knew that the Answers forum platform was not the space the community wanted to gather - Answers is a site designed for <em>support</em>, not community building, and we as the community experts recognized moving to that space would be a detriment. It took <em>a lot</em> of resources from another team, but we involved the volunteer moderators during testing phases to help curate the platform to the community they helped maintain.<br />
<br />
The <em>suggestion</em> of kicking off a Discord server on the same team was met with resistance. I wasn’t the driver of the plan but supported and assisted taking it on as a social space; the application was specifically built for gamers and has a ton of good features for community building - it just made sense. But the decision makers didn’t understand the <em>whys</em> behind it, mostly because they themselves weren’t a true part of the gaming community they were tasked to own. What I’m trying to illustrate here is even if <b>you have an existing community</b>, there is <em>very likely</em> going to come a time in which you will need to <b>build a new community space</b> anyway.<br />
<br />
I love humans. We will gather around a common cause often and the technology we use is no exception. From the company itself to your products, there are often <b>existing communities talking about your work</b> and the business decisions you make. I enjoy finding passionate people who built their community outside of official spaces because then your role will come with a pre-built community. You will often find <b>well-established community members as moderators</b> and there will always be historical chatter about your products - such great data to dig into for customer insights, and if the original posters are still around you have the opportunity to talk to them more about their thoughts.<br />
<br />
Highly technical consumers simply <b>don’t trust companies</b> who step into their self-maintained communities; if you don’t know how to speak to that community, you come across as either tone deaf or a marketing drone. Sometimes you’ll get deeper into a community and find that some moderators, or even some long-time members, believe themselves to be gods. It’s good to do your best to work with them to tone down their ego, but sometimes you have to yeet the ones who are not willing to change.<br />
<br />
The final hurdle that should be tackled when stepping into an existing community is <b>gaining access to administrative tools and metrics</b> for the established platforms. If you don’t have the proper admin/mod access for a lot of social platforms you have no way to really track how well your community is growing. This <em>requires</em> a really close relationship with the moderators of those spaces to either get access to or help with accessing the data. I find <a href="/archived/art-of-empathy">empathy is a top notch skill</a> to build those relationships. 😉<br />
<br />
Now, you’re a newer company or have a new product, or maybe you want to build a new space for your community to congregate. <b>What platform you choose</b> is highly dependent on what kind of community you have - you need to identify how your community communicates with each other, this is key to what platform you end up migrating to. Knowing this will help show your community how much <b>you respect who they are</b> and builds loyalty. Whatever you decide on, the best part is that you get to choose one that has the tools for the metrics <em>you</em> want to track for maintaining the health of the community. Some forum platforms have great customization options when it comes to metrics you can track, so really the sky is the limit.<br />
<br />
Starting with a baby community offers you the opportunity to <b>form close bonds</b> with early community members, most of whom will end up being your biggest supporters worthy of promoting into community leader roles. However, what platform you choose is often based on how many engineering resources you can get; <b>some platforms require developer skills</b> and you may need to either hire an external vendor or pull an internal resource to build the space if you lack those skills.<br />
<br />
imo, this is the best way to start building a community because you get full control of the experience and include early community members in forming a community together - <b>you’re building loyalty</b> (<em>have you recognized a pattern yet?</em>). Going down this path can help to <b>quickly earn the trust of the community</b> and give them the opportunity to share their opinions on shifts early. They see immediately when their opinion is part of shaping a community, but it can still take time to <em>fully</em> earn their trust.<br />
<br />
The part of the process that I’ve noticed causes the most delays in launching a community space is <b>the collaboration across the entire company</b> that is <em>required</em> to launch a community platform. In the big tech world, you often need to work with product, engineering, marketing, comms, maybe fold in customer support/success, leadership, and (the hardest group) <em>legal</em> to get full buy-in on a new platform that represents your company. An experienced community program manager can navigate this and get things signed off with minimal compromises, but some newer to the role may need to compromise on their dream state a little. Understanding all of your platform options should help your story around why the company should invest in doing the work.<br />
<br />
Investigating how communities function is my favorite thing to do starting out in a new role. I get to dig into new information and form new friendships. My time on both the Xbox and Microsoft Edge teams gave me lifelong friends thanks to how I inserted myself into their communities, and it all <b>starts with data</b>. After you get social data, then you get to dig into platform options, what metrics you can track, and build a community program with set goals all at once.<br />
<br />
Next in this series, I’ll detail how to start up communities on various forums platforms, Discord, and Reddit. There’s an aspect of this process I didn’t mention here when you are also advocating for the user voice as a community program manager: social listening. I’ll talk more about the art of this skill in a future post.<br />
<br />
Remember to <b>be empathetic during your interactions</b> with both your colleagues and community members, and you’ll find <b>people will work with you</b> instead of against you while building a new community or forging bonds with an existing one.<br />
<br />
-🧜🏻‍♀️🦄</p>]]></content><author><name>the cyborg</name></author><category term="archived" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[AUTHOR NOTE This was originally posted on my WordPress blog, which I have deleted after migrating the blog's posts to this website in November 2025. Differences from the original are minimal and include: grammatical improvements throughout the post, text formatting changes, adding in more paragraphs to reduce the wall of text, and rephrasing the pros and cons bullets to fit better in the HTML table. building your community A new blog series of mine dedicated to sharing out knowledge on building communities - both from 0 &gt; 1 and stepping into an established community. I plan to include posts about setting up a new social space, community standards, and moderating in the near future; today I’d like to talk about how to start building communities in the first place. The hardest part is knowing where to start - understanding the benefits and downsides of existing communities versus building a brand new space can help. During my time at Microsoft, I became the expert in building and bonding with online communities. I don’t really know exactly how it happened but I befriended people who did the same kind of work I did but for Intune, and I became quite friendly with the Windows Insiders team really early in my role - that’s likely directly related to my notariety as a community expert. I also had great connections on the Xbox Insiders team from my time on Xbox, including one who mentored me on their community building practices for Reddit. I stood up the Edge product group connection forums to build relationships with the volunteer moderators and independent advisors for Microsoft’s Answers site as the first product group to pilot the effort. This led me to meeting up with the supportability team back over on Xbox and advising them of how to go through creating their own product space on Answers to build relationships with the same group of volunteers. Before I exited Microsoft, I had advised the .NET team on how to stand up a preview community program. On the Xbox Ambassador team, I helped launch and admin their community Discord server in 2017, and I’ve owned/moderated a few different servers over the years since then. Unofficially, I helped out in two community servers dedicated to Microsoft in both consumer and enterprise spaces for the Edge team, with one server honoring me with a Community Hero role (mostly because of my shitposting skills 😂). My point is, I’ve been around the community world in a variety of role levels and in this post I want to share some of the pros &amp; cons of stepping into an existing community space as a company representative and standing up an entirely new space for your community to congregate. Note: I will not be giving advice on how to market these spaces - it’s my honest opinion that word of mouth will help these spaces organically grow with you engaging genuinely and honoring your word as a company - or admitting when you are wrong and being honest about product changes. 🫰🏻 There are two different ways one should build or grow a community: either there is an existing community and you want to establish yourself as a company representative to build brand loyalty, or you are going to build up a new space to nurture a baby community from the ground up. There are pros and cons to both of these, but if you think your product doesn’t have an existing community you may be underestimating your users already - I have found communities pre-formed for unlikely products. Existing communities New communities Pros ~ People are already passionate about the product or company ~ Spaces likely have moderators who are trusted ~ Lots of candid feedback from the past can be dove into Pros ~ Unifies the community with the company ~ Direct control over admin and moderation tools for metric tracking ~ Can identify community leaders before promoting them Cons ~ A lot of tech communities don't trust company representatives ~ Moderators or long-time members can have chips on their shoulders ~ Limited access to administrative or moderating tools to the space Cons ~ Engineering resources are needed to stand up custom platforms ~ It takes time to earn trust, candid feedback can be harder to gather ~ Need a lot of collaboration across the company to feel authentic]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Translating user feedback for different internal audiences</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/archived/translating-user-feedback" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Translating user feedback for different internal audiences" /><published>2023-06-20T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-06-20T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/archived/translating%20user%20feedback</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/archived/translating-user-feedback"><![CDATA[<details>
<summary><b>AUTHOR NOTE</b></summary>
<i>This was originally posted on my WordPress blog, which I have deleted after migrating the blog's posts to this website in November 2025. Differences from the original are minimal and include: grammatical improvements throughout the post, adjusting the text formatting, adding in paragraphs to reduce the wall of text, and linking to Jen's bsky profile instead of Xitter.</i>
</details>
<p><br />
If you’ve known me for longer than a week, you’ve heard me talk about my role as a user advocate and how important it is for a company to invest in someone like me. One thing I specialize in is translating “user” to a variety of audiences, something my flavor of autism lets me do by masking into a social group. I’ve always considered myself a social butterfly, easily fitting into every group, making it possible to understand how those different groups communicated and engaged with each other. This superpower thrives in autistic women and is one of the things that often sets them apart from their male counterparts.<br />
<br />
It’s something I <em>unconsciously</em> do when I am introduced to a new group; I absorb how they like to be spoken to by just interacting with and observing people. This makes me incredibly effective at explaining almost anything to a wide range of colleagues, and convince them to fold the feedback into a business decision. A lot of people may know what I’m describing as “social listening” when you account for what my experience is in, but I feel there’s another aspect to it when it’s a part of product decisions instead of marketing - it uses data to <b>improve the product directly</b> rather than determining social content.<br />
<br />
There are <b>two things I do when advocating for a product’s community</b>, a) <b>fight for a single user issue</b> I truly believe needs to be adjusted for the betterment of the product, and b) <b>build a story around complaints/feedback</b> combined with user research to bring about product change. I’ve been successful with both over my career! I once escalated a single report I considered a decent accessibility issue - when using a screen reader on the browser’s themes page, it wasn’t entirely clear what the color was because it <em>only</em> read the theme’s marketing name. I explained to the accessibility champ that a blind person likely won’t know if “mango” meant the color or if there were a collection of mangoes on the screen, and crafted a great user story to help him go to bat with marketing to change the screen reader descriptions.<br />
<br />
On the other side, I partnered with the User Research team at Microsoft to interview under-represented groups and identify pain points with technology, asking questions I designed based on what my community talked about, then drove the presentation of a user story with direct product feedback and related external research about tech in low-income areas to the entire Edge team (which inspired product change to help improve data sync issues).<br />
<br />
There is a <em>very fine line</em> dividing when and how to use these processes; it’s a good combination of <b>trusting your gut</b>, sticking to <b>your principles</b>, and simple <b>experience</b>. It’s hard to tell you exactly which way path you should take because each situation is unique, but in general you want to start your time at a company with building around a collection of voices rather than a single report. Over time, you will learn to identify the single-user battles you want to fight for. Here’s how I have built user stories - and tips on what one can do - to present to my colleagues across a few role types I’ve worked with over my career.<br />
<br />
You first need to <b>understand how users speak</b>. This is often quite different than how engineers, marketing, and product managers speak - users aren’t building a closed-source product and typically don’t know the technical terms of the features in the product. To them, what outsiders colloquially call something in your product <em>is</em> the feature name.<br />
<br />
An excellent example I use is the browser’s omnibox. You have the general users, people who use a browser for every day things, who talk about the “address bar” because that’s what they’ve known for most of the existence of browsers. But you can also have the tech enthusiasts, like developers, bleeding tech users, or sysadmins, who will call tools and features by their technical names because they use those terms in their daily life, so you may hear them say “omnibox”. If you <b>don’t understand the nomenclature</b> that your community is using, you <b><em>cannot translate that feedback to anyone</em></b>, let alone leadership.<br />
<br />
On that note, let me start with <b>leadership</b> audiences. <b>Get to the point fast</b> - you can craft a beautiful story, but if you don’t get through the key points quickly you <em>will</em> lose this audience. Touch on both the positives and negatives of the situation, highlight important data points that support your story, and bring it all together with an elevator pitch of what you believe should be done. The best part about utilizing user feedback in your story is that you have a cheat sheet! You can source your elevator pitch solution directly from your users. 👌🏻<br />
<br />
Some users eloquently explain what they would rather see and it helps one see it from a product perspective - but remember to <b>look at all the data</b> so that you can tell the difference between <em>what your users say</em> and <em>how they use your product</em>. Using data to support your users’ voices will force you to look at the bigger picture and may help you see other, non-obvious solutions to offer to leadership, <em>especially</em> if what users are saying is counter to their behavior. As an early-in-career employee, I presented to leadership after convincing my manager (<em>you know, my leader</em>) that (<em>their</em>) leadership needed to hear what our users were saying. I often worked with the feature owners and engineers to support my story before I got in front of leadership.<br />
<br />
<b>Engineers and product managers</b> can be spoken to essentially the same way in my experience, especially if they built the feature and know the ins and outs. This is why understanding what your users call product features is incredibly important in your role as a feedback owner or customer voice expert. I like arming myself with a ton of information when I approach an engineer or PM.<br />
<br />
To ensure I know precisely what the user is saying before I go to my colleagues, I <b>ask the user deep probing questions</b>. If it’s a bug, I get as much information about when it started and the device info to help with slicing through released versions to find the change that broke. If it’s feedback, especially <em>negative</em> feedback and the user seems very willing to give more details, I probe into how they feel it could best work for them over an active conversation devoted to their user story. Having this conversation helps you <b>have an intimate understanding of what the user wants</b>, and when you have that plus the ability to translate that feedback into internal terms, it <b>sets everyone up for success</b>.<br />
<br />
If there’s a lot to go over, be sure to have your raw data ready, but I find a lot of people really enjoy word clouds to sort verbatim data. It’s amazing how quickly you can throw together a PowerPoint deck for your story and include links to the raw data. When this is properly done, the product managers and engineers know what they can do to alleviate the concerns, and the user had an active hand in shaping the product. 👏🏻 It also builds a lot of trust between you, your teammates, and the community! This is how I tackle my colleagues, and I do this before tackling leadership - sometimes even before I go to my manager.<br />
<br />
One of my favorite things is <b>learning from engineers</b>. I learned a lot about A/V technology in chromium browsers thanks to my time on the Microsoft Edge team - the media team built an internal browser page to help gather details needed for troubleshooting their issues. I escalated issues so often that they decided it would be more beneficial than the risk of exposing the data. Learning from the engineers is <b>very valuable</b> when figuring out how to translate internal terminology to a user. I verify with them when I offer public responses to ensure it makes sense to the engineers in addition to being digestible by the consumer. This way I know that what I translated is accurate, and I <b>learned something new</b> about a complicated piece of software. Win-win!<br />
<br />
Marketing is an interesting one to cover because there’s <b>a variety of marketing partners</b> you may work with. Some you will want to talk to like leadership because <em>they are</em>; more often than not marketing leadership will be in the meetings along with product leadership so you’ll naturally end up treating them similarly. Always make sure that you <b>have explanations for numbers</b> you are presenting because the marketing leaders I have worked with <em>dig much deeper</em> into data than the engineers.<br />
<br />
Now we have traditional marketing and product marketing. When I <b>translate user feedback</b> from a technical community to a <b>traditional marketing manager</b> who is new to tech, I often talk to them like I would a general consumer but also try to explain how users speak versus how we present the brand as a product. I had to learn how to not sound condescending in text when I do this, so that may be something you want to watch for in your own conversations. 😬 In my case, if I felt like I was being too robotic or flat in my response in text, I’d have a teammate look it over for peace of mind. “Hey, do I sound like a dick in this?” - a phrase I became comfortable asking.<br />
<br />
<b>Product marketing managers</b> have been my best allies because many have come from unconventional backgrounds like myself - one of my favorites to work with at Microsoft was a sysadmin before he was a PMM for Commercial GTM. These conversations I had to flip a little - most are tech savvy but don’t know the audience well enough to understand how to market to them, and their responsibilities included doing user research to find new product directions. In these cases, I <b>share feedback from the community</b> to help support what they were digging into after doing competitive analysis on my own - this is an interesting way of influencing product decisions since PMMs often drive new features.<br />
<br />
And then you have <b>consumer and commercial product marketing</b>. 🫠 In my experience, <em>consumer</em> product marketing managers in tech don’t think like regular tech users. They tend to <b>make assumptions</b> based on their predefined audience buckets. I have found that general consumers just don’t give a shit about the technology or what you are putting into the product; only your biggest fans care and those tend to be a more technically-inclined audience. When you approach these types of marketers with community feedback, I’ve found you need to have the product manager who owns the feature on your side for back up (like the themes example at the beginning of this post).<br />
<br />
The <em>commercial</em> product marketing managers I’ve worked with have been my <em>best partnerships</em> as I look over my career. I think that’s largely because they understand the nuances that go into enterprises which are filled with not only technical people setting up the product but non-technical end users. They tend to understand that a lot of enterprises are stuck on older technology, so it’s easier to come to them without translating exact feedback from sysadmins too much. I have found that I need to treat some product marketing managers as if they were new feature owners, normally because they are new to either the company/product or simply aren’t waist deep in the community yet. I worked with product marketing managers for way too many things to actually list here, but I was the <em>only</em> customer voice expert for the Microsoft Edge team and I felt quite comfortable bringing up community concerns without fear of being dismissed.<br />
<br />
I once asked <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/jenmsft.bsky.social">Jen Gentleman</a>, “How do you get people to listen to you with community feedback?” and she responded, “<em>They just do</em>.” This is when I realized that <b>my relationships with my peers</b> were going to be way more <b>valuable</b> than I expected and I needed to win over others. I’ve found that being passionate but humble, detailed yet brief, actively listening and learning when provided valid criticisms of your work, and coming with data to back you up will build up really solid professional relationships with your peers.<br />
<br />
I was known on the Edge team for being a ball of positivity who would get shit done, a great teacher who made people immediately comfortable, and legitimately the heart and soul of the team. It takes work to do this but it’s very important if you want people in any role to listen to you, and I would say that building solid relationships with your colleagues needs to be a <b>top priority</b> when acting as a user advocate. Learning how to speak publicly can help you advocate for your users, making it easier to communicate their needs without faltering.<br />
<br />
A lot of this is advice that I encourage people to seek from their mentors at work. Find a mentor who can educate you in these things, one who will also advocate for you, and you can flourish as a user advocate in any role. Remember to <b>learn how your community speaks</b>, understand and <b>learn how each role</b> at your company <b>likes to be spoken to</b>, ensure you look at your <b>product’s usage data</b> in addition to what your <b>users tell you</b>, and <b>build a foundation of trust</b> with your peers, and you’ll be able to drive product change from your community as a collective or push a single-user report with ease throughout your career. At least in this one’s experience right here. 😉<br />
<br />
-🧜🏻‍♀️🦄</p>]]></content><author><name>the cyborg</name></author><category term="archived" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[AUTHOR NOTE This was originally posted on my WordPress blog, which I have deleted after migrating the blog's posts to this website in November 2025. Differences from the original are minimal and include: grammatical improvements throughout the post, adjusting the text formatting, adding in paragraphs to reduce the wall of text, and linking to Jen's bsky profile instead of Xitter. If you’ve known me for longer than a week, you’ve heard me talk about my role as a user advocate and how important it is for a company to invest in someone like me. One thing I specialize in is translating “user” to a variety of audiences, something my flavor of autism lets me do by masking into a social group. I’ve always considered myself a social butterfly, easily fitting into every group, making it possible to understand how those different groups communicated and engaged with each other. This superpower thrives in autistic women and is one of the things that often sets them apart from their male counterparts. It’s something I unconsciously do when I am introduced to a new group; I absorb how they like to be spoken to by just interacting with and observing people. This makes me incredibly effective at explaining almost anything to a wide range of colleagues, and convince them to fold the feedback into a business decision. A lot of people may know what I’m describing as “social listening” when you account for what my experience is in, but I feel there’s another aspect to it when it’s a part of product decisions instead of marketing - it uses data to improve the product directly rather than determining social content. There are two things I do when advocating for a product’s community, a) fight for a single user issue I truly believe needs to be adjusted for the betterment of the product, and b) build a story around complaints/feedback combined with user research to bring about product change. I’ve been successful with both over my career! I once escalated a single report I considered a decent accessibility issue - when using a screen reader on the browser’s themes page, it wasn’t entirely clear what the color was because it only read the theme’s marketing name. I explained to the accessibility champ that a blind person likely won’t know if “mango” meant the color or if there were a collection of mangoes on the screen, and crafted a great user story to help him go to bat with marketing to change the screen reader descriptions. On the other side, I partnered with the User Research team at Microsoft to interview under-represented groups and identify pain points with technology, asking questions I designed based on what my community talked about, then drove the presentation of a user story with direct product feedback and related external research about tech in low-income areas to the entire Edge team (which inspired product change to help improve data sync issues). There is a very fine line dividing when and how to use these processes; it’s a good combination of trusting your gut, sticking to your principles, and simple experience. It’s hard to tell you exactly which way path you should take because each situation is unique, but in general you want to start your time at a company with building around a collection of voices rather than a single report. Over time, you will learn to identify the single-user battles you want to fight for. Here’s how I have built user stories - and tips on what one can do - to present to my colleagues across a few role types I’ve worked with over my career. You first need to understand how users speak. This is often quite different than how engineers, marketing, and product managers speak - users aren’t building a closed-source product and typically don’t know the technical terms of the features in the product. To them, what outsiders colloquially call something in your product is the feature name. An excellent example I use is the browser’s omnibox. You have the general users, people who use a browser for every day things, who talk about the “address bar” because that’s what they’ve known for most of the existence of browsers. But you can also have the tech enthusiasts, like developers, bleeding tech users, or sysadmins, who will call tools and features by their technical names because they use those terms in their daily life, so you may hear them say “omnibox”. If you don’t understand the nomenclature that your community is using, you cannot translate that feedback to anyone, let alone leadership. On that note, let me start with leadership audiences. Get to the point fast - you can craft a beautiful story, but if you don’t get through the key points quickly you will lose this audience. Touch on both the positives and negatives of the situation, highlight important data points that support your story, and bring it all together with an elevator pitch of what you believe should be done. The best part about utilizing user feedback in your story is that you have a cheat sheet! You can source your elevator pitch solution directly from your users. 👌🏻 Some users eloquently explain what they would rather see and it helps one see it from a product perspective - but remember to look at all the data so that you can tell the difference between what your users say and how they use your product. Using data to support your users’ voices will force you to look at the bigger picture and may help you see other, non-obvious solutions to offer to leadership, especially if what users are saying is counter to their behavior. As an early-in-career employee, I presented to leadership after convincing my manager (you know, my leader) that (their) leadership needed to hear what our users were saying. I often worked with the feature owners and engineers to support my story before I got in front of leadership. Engineers and product managers can be spoken to essentially the same way in my experience, especially if they built the feature and know the ins and outs. This is why understanding what your users call product features is incredibly important in your role as a feedback owner or customer voice expert. I like arming myself with a ton of information when I approach an engineer or PM. To ensure I know precisely what the user is saying before I go to my colleagues, I ask the user deep probing questions. If it’s a bug, I get as much information about when it started and the device info to help with slicing through released versions to find the change that broke. If it’s feedback, especially negative feedback and the user seems very willing to give more details, I probe into how they feel it could best work for them over an active conversation devoted to their user story. Having this conversation helps you have an intimate understanding of what the user wants, and when you have that plus the ability to translate that feedback into internal terms, it sets everyone up for success. If there’s a lot to go over, be sure to have your raw data ready, but I find a lot of people really enjoy word clouds to sort verbatim data. It’s amazing how quickly you can throw together a PowerPoint deck for your story and include links to the raw data. When this is properly done, the product managers and engineers know what they can do to alleviate the concerns, and the user had an active hand in shaping the product. 👏🏻 It also builds a lot of trust between you, your teammates, and the community! This is how I tackle my colleagues, and I do this before tackling leadership - sometimes even before I go to my manager. One of my favorite things is learning from engineers. I learned a lot about A/V technology in chromium browsers thanks to my time on the Microsoft Edge team - the media team built an internal browser page to help gather details needed for troubleshooting their issues. I escalated issues so often that they decided it would be more beneficial than the risk of exposing the data. Learning from the engineers is very valuable when figuring out how to translate internal terminology to a user. I verify with them when I offer public responses to ensure it makes sense to the engineers in addition to being digestible by the consumer. This way I know that what I translated is accurate, and I learned something new about a complicated piece of software. Win-win! Marketing is an interesting one to cover because there’s a variety of marketing partners you may work with. Some you will want to talk to like leadership because they are; more often than not marketing leadership will be in the meetings along with product leadership so you’ll naturally end up treating them similarly. Always make sure that you have explanations for numbers you are presenting because the marketing leaders I have worked with dig much deeper into data than the engineers. Now we have traditional marketing and product marketing. When I translate user feedback from a technical community to a traditional marketing manager who is new to tech, I often talk to them like I would a general consumer but also try to explain how users speak versus how we present the brand as a product. I had to learn how to not sound condescending in text when I do this, so that may be something you want to watch for in your own conversations. 😬 In my case, if I felt like I was being too robotic or flat in my response in text, I’d have a teammate look it over for peace of mind. “Hey, do I sound like a dick in this?” - a phrase I became comfortable asking. Product marketing managers have been my best allies because many have come from unconventional backgrounds like myself - one of my favorites to work with at Microsoft was a sysadmin before he was a PMM for Commercial GTM. These conversations I had to flip a little - most are tech savvy but don’t know the audience well enough to understand how to market to them, and their responsibilities included doing user research to find new product directions. In these cases, I share feedback from the community to help support what they were digging into after doing competitive analysis on my own - this is an interesting way of influencing product decisions since PMMs often drive new features. And then you have consumer and commercial product marketing. 🫠 In my experience, consumer product marketing managers in tech don’t think like regular tech users. They tend to make assumptions based on their predefined audience buckets. I have found that general consumers just don’t give a shit about the technology or what you are putting into the product; only your biggest fans care and those tend to be a more technically-inclined audience. When you approach these types of marketers with community feedback, I’ve found you need to have the product manager who owns the feature on your side for back up (like the themes example at the beginning of this post). The commercial product marketing managers I’ve worked with have been my best partnerships as I look over my career. I think that’s largely because they understand the nuances that go into enterprises which are filled with not only technical people setting up the product but non-technical end users. They tend to understand that a lot of enterprises are stuck on older technology, so it’s easier to come to them without translating exact feedback from sysadmins too much. I have found that I need to treat some product marketing managers as if they were new feature owners, normally because they are new to either the company/product or simply aren’t waist deep in the community yet. I worked with product marketing managers for way too many things to actually list here, but I was the only customer voice expert for the Microsoft Edge team and I felt quite comfortable bringing up community concerns without fear of being dismissed. I once asked Jen Gentleman, “How do you get people to listen to you with community feedback?” and she responded, “They just do.” This is when I realized that my relationships with my peers were going to be way more valuable than I expected and I needed to win over others. I’ve found that being passionate but humble, detailed yet brief, actively listening and learning when provided valid criticisms of your work, and coming with data to back you up will build up really solid professional relationships with your peers. I was known on the Edge team for being a ball of positivity who would get shit done, a great teacher who made people immediately comfortable, and legitimately the heart and soul of the team. It takes work to do this but it’s very important if you want people in any role to listen to you, and I would say that building solid relationships with your colleagues needs to be a top priority when acting as a user advocate. Learning how to speak publicly can help you advocate for your users, making it easier to communicate their needs without faltering. A lot of this is advice that I encourage people to seek from their mentors at work. Find a mentor who can educate you in these things, one who will also advocate for you, and you can flourish as a user advocate in any role. Remember to learn how your community speaks, understand and learn how each role at your company likes to be spoken to, ensure you look at your product’s usage data in addition to what your users tell you, and build a foundation of trust with your peers, and you’ll be able to drive product change from your community as a collective or push a single-user report with ease throughout your career. At least in this one’s experience right here. 😉 -🧜🏻‍♀️🦄]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Let’s normalize sensory needs!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/archived/normalize-sensory-needs" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Let’s normalize sensory needs!" /><published>2023-05-24T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-05-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/archived/normalize%20sensory%20needs</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/archived/normalize-sensory-needs"><![CDATA[<details>
<summary><b>AUTHOR NOTE</b></summary>
<i>This was originally posted on my WordPress blog, which I have deleted after migrating the blog's posts to this website in November 2025. Differences from the original are minimal and include: grammatical adjustments throughout the post, adding paragraphs to reduce the wall of text, changing the phrasing of a couple sentences to make more sense, text formatting changes, and including my Bluesky profile link as a way for people to reach me. My "things I do to help reduce their impact" are basically just communicating my needs to those around me and cognitive behavior therapy. Why did I just save you from reading this whole article? I don't know, but it felt important to let y'all know that this post barely has a point.</i> 🤣
</details>
<p><br />
May is Mental Health Month, and for my first post <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/missyquarry_instead-of-applying-to-jobs-or-working-on-activity-7061872820724629504-VZHy/">since I got back from Hawai’i</a> I want to talk about sensory needs. I have utilized coping techniques to adjust to my sensory issues without realizing it in the past; now I’m more self-aware and self-advocate for my needs whenever I can. Taking care of these needs reduces the anxiety induced from being overstimulated.<br />
<br />
To help normalize what I and others go through, I want to share my own sensory issues, some things I do to help reduce their impact on my mental health, and some resources you may find interesting if you want to read more. Sensory processing disorders can spread across several different mental health diagnoses, and it can appear that you’re “sensitive” to others.<br />
<br />
I have issues across a few different senses and some are basically chicken/egg scenarios - one will trigger another. Sounds/noise can be interesting since it depends on the level of how prickly my ears want to be. For the most part, loud sounds (regardless if I am ready for them or not) and wind blowing over my ears are the worst offenders. I can hear certain low frequencies quite loudly and they take over my hearing, sometimes inducing a panic attack if it’s low enough. I also get overstimulated by being around large and loud crowds for too long, but this highly depends on how sensitive I happen to be that day.<br />
<br />
I can pick out sounds easily just by focusing on it and, as a side effect from my ADHD, I sometimes get distracted by what I hear. I’ve yelled down the hallway on more than one occasion at co-workers to participate in conversations they didn’t realize I could hear. <b>Noise cancelling headphones are a must for me</b> - I cannot go back to <em>not</em> having any. When I need to focus on a project at home or at work, I put on my Bose 700s (I love these things) and turn on some stream noises from my iPad with noise cancellation all the way up. If I need to block out what’s happening around me because it all feels overwhelming, I step into a quieter room by myself and put on some bangin’ music fit for my mood at the time.<br />
<br />
I didn’t realize I had touch sensory problems until I went through the interview for my formal diagnosis. My son’s behavioral therapy helped me understand the different needs for the spectrum of touch issues - a soft pressure around the body similar to a hug helps reduce anxiety, but you can also feel that single hair tickling under your clothes and can_not_ find it driving you more mad than normal. My son has a weighted blanket because he likes the sense of pressure on him to help calm him down; other pressure techniques without a blanket can be soft squeezes down the arms or a tight squeezy hug.<br />
<br />
I <em>do not</em> like the feeling of being smothered so the idea of a full weighted blanket makes me uneasy - I may be a little claustrophobic but not diagnosed - however I do have a weighted stuffed animal from <a href="https://www.moonpals.com">Moon Pals</a>. I sit this on my lap when I am working and need some grounding or focus.<br />
<br />
Most of my touch sensory issues are around things touching my skin with some food textures thrown in for good measure. I really dislike most meat unless it’s ground up - the sinewy texture is <em>awful</em>. I dislike my hands being <em>any form of slimy</em>, if my hair is down you may often see me pulling it to the side to make sure all <em>the loose hairs are removed</em>, I adjust seams in my clothing to ensure it fits on <em>just</em> the right spot, and can <em>feel my contacts</em> on my bottom eyelids if they are too dry (<em>gods</em>, that’s the weirdest sensation).<br />
<br />
The best thing for me to do in these cases is simply <b>avoid the scenarios</b> that cause most of these. I learned to live with constantly checking for and removing hair that tickles me and adjusting my seams - that’s just part of my autism and I <em>will not</em> suppress harmless ticks to fit in. I may not like a texture or a feeling on my skin but I am no longer worried about how others view me when I make small adjustments like this.<br />
<br />
I also have visual sensory issues! My eyes are surprisingly sensitive to the sun, I need to wear sunglasses most of the time when I am outside during the day - even when it’s cloudy. The others are some pretty typical autistic qualities: if the food on my plate is a different type (wet/dry, meat/produce) it <em>cannot touch</em>, everything needs to be <em>where I put it</em> in the house, and I will <em>re-organize an entire room</em> if I feel like things don’t fit right anymore.<br />
<br />
Earlier in my adulthood there was no connection to the autism for these things so we called me <em>picky</em> or <em>neurotic</em>. Now I have coping skills for all of these. I now <em>mostly</em> accept when food touches (you may catch me pushing things apart before I eat it, though), I don’t freak out <em>externally</em> when things aren’t put away or cleaned the right way, and I <em>include my husband</em> in my re-organizing efforts instead of just doing it without him. You bet your sweet ass that on highly sensitive days it’s harder for me to use these skills, but believe me when I say I’m thankful I practice them often.<br />
<br />
I may be forgetting some things but this is a decent overview of my own sensory issues and a few techniques I use to cope. Hopefully this helps you recognize if you have your own sensory needs or when you see someone else using their own coping skills.<br />
<br />
If you would like to learn more about sensory processing disorders, <a href="https://www.understood.org/articles/understanding-sensory-processing-issues">Understood.org</a> is a wonderful, free resource that was introduced to me by my son’s behavior specialist. To learn a little more about infrasound and how it impacts mammals, I find <a href="https://www.strangerdimensions.com/2013/06/21/infrasound-the-fear-frequency/">this is a decent</a> overview of why anxiety happens (there’s not much research around this in humans yet). I’m an open book, feel free to <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/adorablecyb.org">ask me anything</a> if you have any questions, too, I’m always happy to chat about ways to reduce sensory processing anxiety. 😊<br />
<br />
-🧜🏻‍♀️🦄</p>]]></content><author><name>the cyborg</name></author><category term="archived" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[AUTHOR NOTE This was originally posted on my WordPress blog, which I have deleted after migrating the blog's posts to this website in November 2025. Differences from the original are minimal and include: grammatical adjustments throughout the post, adding paragraphs to reduce the wall of text, changing the phrasing of a couple sentences to make more sense, text formatting changes, and including my Bluesky profile link as a way for people to reach me. My "things I do to help reduce their impact" are basically just communicating my needs to those around me and cognitive behavior therapy. Why did I just save you from reading this whole article? I don't know, but it felt important to let y'all know that this post barely has a point. 🤣 May is Mental Health Month, and for my first post since I got back from Hawai’i I want to talk about sensory needs. I have utilized coping techniques to adjust to my sensory issues without realizing it in the past; now I’m more self-aware and self-advocate for my needs whenever I can. Taking care of these needs reduces the anxiety induced from being overstimulated. To help normalize what I and others go through, I want to share my own sensory issues, some things I do to help reduce their impact on my mental health, and some resources you may find interesting if you want to read more. Sensory processing disorders can spread across several different mental health diagnoses, and it can appear that you’re “sensitive” to others. I have issues across a few different senses and some are basically chicken/egg scenarios - one will trigger another. Sounds/noise can be interesting since it depends on the level of how prickly my ears want to be. For the most part, loud sounds (regardless if I am ready for them or not) and wind blowing over my ears are the worst offenders. I can hear certain low frequencies quite loudly and they take over my hearing, sometimes inducing a panic attack if it’s low enough. I also get overstimulated by being around large and loud crowds for too long, but this highly depends on how sensitive I happen to be that day. I can pick out sounds easily just by focusing on it and, as a side effect from my ADHD, I sometimes get distracted by what I hear. I’ve yelled down the hallway on more than one occasion at co-workers to participate in conversations they didn’t realize I could hear. Noise cancelling headphones are a must for me - I cannot go back to not having any. When I need to focus on a project at home or at work, I put on my Bose 700s (I love these things) and turn on some stream noises from my iPad with noise cancellation all the way up. If I need to block out what’s happening around me because it all feels overwhelming, I step into a quieter room by myself and put on some bangin’ music fit for my mood at the time. I didn’t realize I had touch sensory problems until I went through the interview for my formal diagnosis. My son’s behavioral therapy helped me understand the different needs for the spectrum of touch issues - a soft pressure around the body similar to a hug helps reduce anxiety, but you can also feel that single hair tickling under your clothes and can_not_ find it driving you more mad than normal. My son has a weighted blanket because he likes the sense of pressure on him to help calm him down; other pressure techniques without a blanket can be soft squeezes down the arms or a tight squeezy hug. I do not like the feeling of being smothered so the idea of a full weighted blanket makes me uneasy - I may be a little claustrophobic but not diagnosed - however I do have a weighted stuffed animal from Moon Pals. I sit this on my lap when I am working and need some grounding or focus. Most of my touch sensory issues are around things touching my skin with some food textures thrown in for good measure. I really dislike most meat unless it’s ground up - the sinewy texture is awful. I dislike my hands being any form of slimy, if my hair is down you may often see me pulling it to the side to make sure all the loose hairs are removed, I adjust seams in my clothing to ensure it fits on just the right spot, and can feel my contacts on my bottom eyelids if they are too dry (gods, that’s the weirdest sensation). The best thing for me to do in these cases is simply avoid the scenarios that cause most of these. I learned to live with constantly checking for and removing hair that tickles me and adjusting my seams - that’s just part of my autism and I will not suppress harmless ticks to fit in. I may not like a texture or a feeling on my skin but I am no longer worried about how others view me when I make small adjustments like this. I also have visual sensory issues! My eyes are surprisingly sensitive to the sun, I need to wear sunglasses most of the time when I am outside during the day - even when it’s cloudy. The others are some pretty typical autistic qualities: if the food on my plate is a different type (wet/dry, meat/produce) it cannot touch, everything needs to be where I put it in the house, and I will re-organize an entire room if I feel like things don’t fit right anymore. Earlier in my adulthood there was no connection to the autism for these things so we called me picky or neurotic. Now I have coping skills for all of these. I now mostly accept when food touches (you may catch me pushing things apart before I eat it, though), I don’t freak out externally when things aren’t put away or cleaned the right way, and I include my husband in my re-organizing efforts instead of just doing it without him. You bet your sweet ass that on highly sensitive days it’s harder for me to use these skills, but believe me when I say I’m thankful I practice them often. I may be forgetting some things but this is a decent overview of my own sensory issues and a few techniques I use to cope. Hopefully this helps you recognize if you have your own sensory needs or when you see someone else using their own coping skills. If you would like to learn more about sensory processing disorders, Understood.org is a wonderful, free resource that was introduced to me by my son’s behavior specialist. To learn a little more about infrasound and how it impacts mammals, I find this is a decent overview of why anxiety happens (there’s not much research around this in humans yet). I’m an open book, feel free to ask me anything if you have any questions, too, I’m always happy to chat about ways to reduce sensory processing anxiety. 😊 -🧜🏻‍♀️🦄]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Social media metrics are NOT community building metrics</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/archived/social-media-is-not-community-building" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Social media metrics are NOT community building metrics" /><published>2023-04-24T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-04-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/archived/social%20media%20is%20not%20community%20building</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/archived/social-media-is-not-community-building"><![CDATA[<details>
<summary><b>AUTHOR NOTE</b></summary>
<i>This was originally posted on my WordPress blog, which I have deleted after migrating the blog's posts to this website in November 2025. Differences from the original are minimal and include: grammatical corrections throughout the post, adding in paragraph breaks to remove the wall of text, rearranging the sentences around the metrics I was held to at XCS, removing seemingly weird emojis, hyperlinking to sections for easier navigation within the post, clarifying how watching viewers drop off increases completion rate, and there are a couple Author's Notes added to provide some context.</i>
</details>
<p><br />
“Hey, can we track our community engagement efforts with the engagement rate of the social content we publish?” <em>Ugh</em>.<br />
<br />
Yes, but also <b><em>no</em></b>. 🙄<br />
<br />
The biggest problem I see right now with companies who say they listen to their customers is that most of them still sit community management under traditional marketing and undervalue its existence. We have built this thought in the tech industry that managing a community is just marketing for reach and getting more followers, but it’s truly <em>so much more than that</em>, and <a href="https://textslashplain.com/2022/05/18/thoughts-on-impact/">it’s incredibly hard to measure</a> because people in charge do not understand its impact without “hard data”.<br />
<br />
<em>Because feelings and real conversations aren’t valid, obviously.</em><br />
<br />
I’ve been finding more and more product marketing managers understand that brand loyalty is important, but they still sit on more traditional marketing teams and beholden to archaic fluff numbers. In fact, the DevRel world has it right where <a href="https://www.swyx.io/measuring-devrel">your north star when building a community</a> should be <b>monthly active users</b>, and everything you do falls into how that number is affected.<br />
<br />
I’ve had to deal with metrics in most of my roles, the most notable are <b><em>ridiculous</em> call center KPIs</b>. Setting a goal of completing a support call within 10 minutes (if you’re lucky) is absolute ass, with nearly no room to do wrap up notes aftercall and often getting a floor supe coming around past 12 minutes with a board that says “You’re over time!” These are metrics that you are keeping for someone you never interact with, it’s a really disjointed relationship between support and those who make decisions.<br />
<br />
We had metrics when I worked on the Xbox Support forums reviewing around 400+ posts a week using an extension in Chrome to track our work. We, uh, weren’t really held to them. 😆 We instead focused heavily on <b>quality over quantity</b>, holding ourselves above the standard type of support by providing each other meaningful coachings on opportunities for improvement. It was this experience and kind of “metric” that I set up for myself and my direct reports on the Edge team; we also used CSAT since our goal was also making sure people were happy.<br />
<br />
I am <em>intimately</em> aware of social media metrics and here to tell you: <b>most of them are purely vanity numbers</b>. They have no real value other than what kind of content performs better than others; you can get <a href="https://www.howtogeek.com/721651/what-does-ratio-mean-on-social-media/">ratioed</a> and still think you performed well because the replies help increase engagement rate, positive or negative. The <b>context is missing</b> in that data, and it’s <em>the most important aspect</em> of it. My opinion is that companies need someone who can analyze this data as a whole to create a story from it and explain the impact it could have on a brand - for better or for worse.<br />
<br />
<a href="https://blog.hootsuite.com/social-media-metrics/">Hootsuite posted an article</a> about the key things you need track for social media metrics and what bothers me is that they not only numbered the list labeled as “the most important metrics”, they put sentiment and share of voice as the last two despite having CSAT and NPS higher on the list. Numbering a list instead of using bullet points gives a false sense of ranking, so this looks like they are devaluing these two items that provides so much context for the rest of the numbers.<br />
<br />
That rubs me the wrong way, so I decided to go through the list and explain whether I feel a metric is a vanity number or if it is truly valuable - but in a ranking that makes more sense to me for a role focusing on community building and brand loyalty.
<br />
<br /></p>
<h3 id="social-share-of-voice-ssov">social share of voice (SSoV)</h3>
<p>Your share of voice is how many people are talking about your brand compared to your competitors, and it’s one of the most important things to pay attention to when building a community. You want to know what they think of your competition and how often they are talking about both of you. You can listen to both direct (with the brand) and indirect (without the brand) conversations, I find combining both helps out the most. A lot of tools don’t do this well yet, but with better AI coming into the tech world and the current open source solutions, it’s only a matter of time before this is easier to do.<br />
<br />
<em>~ How I use this</em>: When investigating a community to find strengths and weaknesses; health of community reporting; competitive research for product insights.<br />
<em>~ Where I won’t use this</em>: I love this metric in community building and brand recognition, I’ll use it wherever I can!
<br />
<br /></p>
<h3 id="social-sentiment">social sentiment</h3>
<p>Aha, <b>my expertise</b> - how happy or meh your users are about you on social media. Hootsuite says you need help calculating this with tools to which I say, BAH. Supporting a brand that is a common word (<em>edge</em>) was not something that even tools could help with without a ton of hand holding, so I manually adjusted sentiment on a <em>weekly</em> basis. To my credit, I have boosted processing thanks to my flavor of autism and can analyze context faster than most others. I look forward to the ML improvements in the near future with the wider adoption of conversational AIs like new Bing and Bard, because this whole process was something I fought to improve within Microsoft for several years (Sprinklr sucks at contextualizing sentiment to a product with a common word). If you just read verbatims from a sample of mentions, the tool you use is your brain’s ability to see context.<br />
<br /></p>
<details>
<summary><b>AUTHOR'S NOTE, Nov 2025</b></summary>
<i>lmaoooooo jesus fuck i pretended to be hopeful about generative AI??? what the fuck missy lol</i>
</details>
<p><br />
<em>~ How I use this</em>: In every aspect of what I do - sentiment is often an afterthought, I make it the forefront.<br />
<em>~ When I won’t use this</em>: This metric can show how happy people are with your product, your communications, your changes, your content, everything - <em>use it</em>.
<br />
<br /></p>
<h3 id="audience-growth-rate">audience growth rate</h3>
<p>What you can also think of as follower growth rate, this shows how quickly your community is building or failing. This is one of the more important metrics to keep track of as it shows the health of your community at a macro level. When you first start a community, your growth rate is going to be incredibly high due to a small community and taper off as your community gets bigger. It’s important to remember that as you build up your goals for your new community or are taking one over that already has a following.<br />
<br />
<em>~ How I use this</em>: With managers or leadership for how well the community is maintained; as a supplement to Sentiment and CSAT in health of community reporting.<br />
<em>~ Where I won’t use this</em>: With feature owners on communications we collaborated on - they don’t need the stress of if they impacted our community’s health, it’s ultimately my responsibility.
<br />
<br /></p>
<h3 id="customer-satisfaction-csat-score">customer satisfaction (CSAT) score</h3>
<p>This one I use often because a lot of community building is making sure they are happy (and the way I build communities is being part support). It’s hard to collect, though - most people you help won’t provide this data so it’s not a full picture and it’s an overused form of surveying users who are done with seeing it. I’ve built CSAT surveys for individual employees and program-wide to gather this data; as long as you have an open text box that allows them to give context for their selection you can get some great insights from this. It may be overused, but it’s also the most widely recognized.<br />
<br />
<em>~ How I use this</em>: Health of community reporting; primary KPI for success of engagement; individual success.<br />
<em>~ Where I won’t use this</em>: With feature owners and marketing partners - this is solely my responsibility and the metric doesn’t help either of these types of colleagues.
<br />
<br /></p>
<h3 id="net-promoter-score-nps">net promoter score (NPS)</h3>
<p>NPS is that whole “how likely would you recommend” set of questions, and it’s widely used. The problem is that it’s not actually a good metric by itself and most of the questions asked are leading. I <a href="https://bweinstein.medium.com/moving-beyond-the-net-promoter-score-9b560f3767ba">prefer using alternative questions</a> like, “In the last <em><strong>x time frame</strong></em>, have you considered switching products to our competitor? [<em>Yes/No</em>]”, which can help identify loyalty better than, “Would you recommend my product?” Another way this can be asked to be specific to your community is, “Have you had a community interaction in the last <strong><em>x time frame</em></strong> that made you think of leaving the community? [<em>Yes/No</em>]”. Including an open text box will allow users to tell you exactly where things are going wrong for them. The 1-10 scale is incredibly archaic and I dislike using it, the explicit binary answer gives you a clear picture of your promoters and detractors.<br />
<br />
<em>~ How I use this</em>: Health of community reporting; primary KPI for success of brand recognition; success of a community program overall.<br />
<em>~ Where I won’t use this</em>: Individual success - while we build brand recognition, this metric is representative of the product or community overall and not an individual.
<br />
<br /></p>
<h3 id="amplification-rate">amplification rate</h3>
<p>This is essentially how much your followers are sharing <em>your</em> content specifically. Not to be confused with <a href="#engagement-rate">engagement rate</a>, it shows how your <a href="#reach">reach</a> is increasing. This is better to track than engagement rate because in community building you are trying to increase brand recognition in which this can correlate. Additionally, those who are the largest contributors to this metric can be considered your superfans you pull in. The type of data you have access to for a social platform determines if you can track this easily or not, but I think Orbit.love is one of the best ways to track this - I wish I was able to implement their product for Edge.<br />
<br /></p>
<details>
<summary><b>AUTHOR'S NOTE, Nov 2025</b></summary>
<i>orbit.love no longer seems to exist, which is pretty sad. It was <a href="https://blog.postman.com/announcing-postman-has-acquired-orbit/">acquired by Postman</a> in April 2024, shortly after I started working for Nabu Casa, but now listed as part of <a href="https://jetrockets.com/portfolio/orbitlove">JetRockets' portfolio</a>. From what I can tell, this is just another open source victim of being gobbled up by the tech industry.</i> 😔
</details>
<p><br />
<em>~ How I use this</em>: With feature owners whose content I am helping amplify; health of community reporting; in presentations about brand-damaging content.<br />
<em>~ Where I won’t use this</em>: With leadership audiences <em>regularly</em> - in cases where brand damage occurs, they need to understand how fast it spread, though.
<br />
<br /></p>
<h3 id="engagement-rate">engagement Rate</h3>
<p>As I explained at the beginning of the post, engagement rate is just how much people engage with your content. Likes, shares, and comments all contribute to this and weigh the same against the metric. It’s useless by itself but good to look at in combination with sentiment as you watch the health of your community, and there are way too many ways to calculate this. This is why I prefer <a href="#amplification-rate">amplification rate</a> over than engagement rate.<br />
<br />
<em>~ How I use this</em>: With marketing partners during major industry events; health of community reporting to the team.<br />
<em>~ Where I won’t use this</em>: With leadership audiences - they don’t look at the bigger picture of this number and often ignore when negative context is included.
<br />
<br /></p>
<h3 id="video-views-and-video-completion-rate">video views and video completion rate</h3>
<p>I am combining these two as they need to be together if you are going to use them. These are useful if you are creating video content for your community like fireside chats with your colleagues or walkthroughs for how to use your product. Views are calculated differently on each platform, so using views and completion time together shows a good picture of how well the content landed with your community. It’s also a great indication of how long you should be making your videos - optimizing the length of your videos helps with increasing completion rate.<br />
<br />
<em>~ How I use this</em>: With marketing partners and feature owners whose content I am helping amplify; when planning out a content calendar.<br />
<em>~ Where I won’t use this</em>: Health of community reporting - this just shows how well your content performs at that time; at the leadership level, they should not care how well your video performed.
<br />
<br /></p>
<h3 id="reach">reach</h3>
<p>This is an easy metric to track, it’s simply how many people see your content and every tool out there can help show you it these days. You can keep an eye on the percentage who are followers and non-followers, however this metric really just shows how well your content performs combined with the size of your active following. An example of why this is bad to focus on: If your content goes viral in a negative way, <em>you’re still getting that reach</em>.<br />
<br />
<em>~ How I use this</em>: With feature owners whose content I am helping amplify; with marketing partners during major industry events.<br />
<em>~ Where I won’t use this</em>: With leadership audiences - they typically don’t grasp how reach works, and the conversations about its value tend to be circular.
<br />
<br /></p>
<h3 id="impressions">impressions</h3>
<p>Another confusing metric, impressions are how many times someone <em>saw</em> your content. An easy example is blog views - you can see how many unique people have visited your site and how many views it has had in total, and views will nearly always be higher than visits (unless you somehow maintain a 1:1 ratio). This means people keep coming back to what you’re talking about, which can be great to track, but without any other context this number doesn’t do much.<br />
<br />
<em>~ How I use this</em>: 🫣<br />
<em>~ Where I won’t use this</em>: With anyone, I hate this metric.
<br />
<br /></p>
<h3 id="virality-rate">virality rate</h3>
<p>Now we’re just making up metrics, aren’t we? Gotta find something to justify your TikTok account? This is the number of shares (<a href="#amplification-rate">amplification</a>) divided by the number of impressions. This is useless for community building and brand recognition - like <a href="#reach">reach</a>, your virality rate means <em>nothing</em> without context.<br />
<br />
<em>~ How I use this</em>: 🫣<br />
<em>~ Where I won’t use this</em>: With anyone, this is a vanity metric.
<br />
<br /></p>
<h3 id="return-on-investment-metrics">return on investment metrics</h3>
<p>Click-through rate (CTR), conversion rate, cost-per-click (CPC), and cost per thousand impressions (CPM) are all almost exclusively social media metrics for paid content and what most leadership teams <em>incorrectly</em> consider community engagement metrics. I am against using these for community building because I think it’s gross justifying community content by how much it costs; content that is liked by the community but not “performing well” tends to be pushed aside for content that can prove it is earning the company money or returning value through these metrics. CTR can be used for organic (not paid) content to see how well you are encouraging people to go to the bigger picture and off the social platform you posted on, but that’s the extent of its usefulness - you can get that same traffic data from the website you are pointing to as the views and click sources.<br />
<br />
<em>~ How I use these</em>: When pitching a new content series to be produced with marketing or teammates - I use them as goals based on historical ranges of the cost.<br />
<em>~ Where I won’t use these</em>: Justifying 1:1 engagement with the community; health of community reporting - both of these should just roll into the salary of the employee as your ROI.<br />
<br />
The way I manage communities has me focus on its <b>audience growth</b> (with higher goals earlier in a community, lowering as the community grows) and <b>sentiment shifts</b> (diving into what is driving negative or positive sentiment over a specified percentage of volume, including share of voice). Everything else rolls into improving these really well.<br />
<br />
To show impact on the product as a feedback loop owner (as an engagement manager should be), I track the completion of feedback requests (including sentiment on the implementation of said feedback) and as much metadata about bugs escalated as possible (where it came from, link to other reports, the history of the item, and linking to bugs the engineers or feature owners own). I try to utilize CSAT and NPS as the bigger picture presented to leadership - a set of numbers that they can easily understand.<br />
<br />
Overall, the article about Measuring DevRel linked at the beginning of this word vomit is great advice for building up <em>any</em> community, not only developer-focused ones, since it digs into the specialty of the relationship owner and how to effectively do and measure each specialty. They give a really good picture as to what works and what doesn’t when it comes to community building. The author doesn’t agree with my take on NPS, but they also call out using a different question than the generic one is better than nothing.<br />
<br />
Some of my opinions here are hot takes and marketing partners I’ve told these to in the past were surprised at my opinion having been a long time community manager. Sure, you want to measure how well your content performs on social media, but ultimately how well your content performs doesn’t explain the macrosituation of your product - <em>only how well your team can make high-performing social media content</em>.<br />
<br />
-🧜‍♀️🦄</p>]]></content><author><name>the cyborg</name></author><category term="archived" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[AUTHOR NOTE This was originally posted on my WordPress blog, which I have deleted after migrating the blog's posts to this website in November 2025. Differences from the original are minimal and include: grammatical corrections throughout the post, adding in paragraph breaks to remove the wall of text, rearranging the sentences around the metrics I was held to at XCS, removing seemingly weird emojis, hyperlinking to sections for easier navigation within the post, clarifying how watching viewers drop off increases completion rate, and there are a couple Author's Notes added to provide some context. “Hey, can we track our community engagement efforts with the engagement rate of the social content we publish?” Ugh. Yes, but also no. 🙄 The biggest problem I see right now with companies who say they listen to their customers is that most of them still sit community management under traditional marketing and undervalue its existence. We have built this thought in the tech industry that managing a community is just marketing for reach and getting more followers, but it’s truly so much more than that, and it’s incredibly hard to measure because people in charge do not understand its impact without “hard data”. Because feelings and real conversations aren’t valid, obviously. I’ve been finding more and more product marketing managers understand that brand loyalty is important, but they still sit on more traditional marketing teams and beholden to archaic fluff numbers. In fact, the DevRel world has it right where your north star when building a community should be monthly active users, and everything you do falls into how that number is affected. I’ve had to deal with metrics in most of my roles, the most notable are ridiculous call center KPIs. Setting a goal of completing a support call within 10 minutes (if you’re lucky) is absolute ass, with nearly no room to do wrap up notes aftercall and often getting a floor supe coming around past 12 minutes with a board that says “You’re over time!” These are metrics that you are keeping for someone you never interact with, it’s a really disjointed relationship between support and those who make decisions. We had metrics when I worked on the Xbox Support forums reviewing around 400+ posts a week using an extension in Chrome to track our work. We, uh, weren’t really held to them. 😆 We instead focused heavily on quality over quantity, holding ourselves above the standard type of support by providing each other meaningful coachings on opportunities for improvement. It was this experience and kind of “metric” that I set up for myself and my direct reports on the Edge team; we also used CSAT since our goal was also making sure people were happy. I am intimately aware of social media metrics and here to tell you: most of them are purely vanity numbers. They have no real value other than what kind of content performs better than others; you can get ratioed and still think you performed well because the replies help increase engagement rate, positive or negative. The context is missing in that data, and it’s the most important aspect of it. My opinion is that companies need someone who can analyze this data as a whole to create a story from it and explain the impact it could have on a brand - for better or for worse. Hootsuite posted an article about the key things you need track for social media metrics and what bothers me is that they not only numbered the list labeled as “the most important metrics”, they put sentiment and share of voice as the last two despite having CSAT and NPS higher on the list. Numbering a list instead of using bullet points gives a false sense of ranking, so this looks like they are devaluing these two items that provides so much context for the rest of the numbers. That rubs me the wrong way, so I decided to go through the list and explain whether I feel a metric is a vanity number or if it is truly valuable - but in a ranking that makes more sense to me for a role focusing on community building and brand loyalty. social share of voice (SSoV) Your share of voice is how many people are talking about your brand compared to your competitors, and it’s one of the most important things to pay attention to when building a community. You want to know what they think of your competition and how often they are talking about both of you. You can listen to both direct (with the brand) and indirect (without the brand) conversations, I find combining both helps out the most. A lot of tools don’t do this well yet, but with better AI coming into the tech world and the current open source solutions, it’s only a matter of time before this is easier to do. ~ How I use this: When investigating a community to find strengths and weaknesses; health of community reporting; competitive research for product insights. ~ Where I won’t use this: I love this metric in community building and brand recognition, I’ll use it wherever I can! social sentiment Aha, my expertise - how happy or meh your users are about you on social media. Hootsuite says you need help calculating this with tools to which I say, BAH. Supporting a brand that is a common word (edge) was not something that even tools could help with without a ton of hand holding, so I manually adjusted sentiment on a weekly basis. To my credit, I have boosted processing thanks to my flavor of autism and can analyze context faster than most others. I look forward to the ML improvements in the near future with the wider adoption of conversational AIs like new Bing and Bard, because this whole process was something I fought to improve within Microsoft for several years (Sprinklr sucks at contextualizing sentiment to a product with a common word). If you just read verbatims from a sample of mentions, the tool you use is your brain’s ability to see context. AUTHOR'S NOTE, Nov 2025 lmaoooooo jesus fuck i pretended to be hopeful about generative AI??? what the fuck missy lol ~ How I use this: In every aspect of what I do - sentiment is often an afterthought, I make it the forefront. ~ When I won’t use this: This metric can show how happy people are with your product, your communications, your changes, your content, everything - use it. audience growth rate What you can also think of as follower growth rate, this shows how quickly your community is building or failing. This is one of the more important metrics to keep track of as it shows the health of your community at a macro level. When you first start a community, your growth rate is going to be incredibly high due to a small community and taper off as your community gets bigger. It’s important to remember that as you build up your goals for your new community or are taking one over that already has a following. ~ How I use this: With managers or leadership for how well the community is maintained; as a supplement to Sentiment and CSAT in health of community reporting. ~ Where I won’t use this: With feature owners on communications we collaborated on - they don’t need the stress of if they impacted our community’s health, it’s ultimately my responsibility. customer satisfaction (CSAT) score This one I use often because a lot of community building is making sure they are happy (and the way I build communities is being part support). It’s hard to collect, though - most people you help won’t provide this data so it’s not a full picture and it’s an overused form of surveying users who are done with seeing it. I’ve built CSAT surveys for individual employees and program-wide to gather this data; as long as you have an open text box that allows them to give context for their selection you can get some great insights from this. It may be overused, but it’s also the most widely recognized. ~ How I use this: Health of community reporting; primary KPI for success of engagement; individual success. ~ Where I won’t use this: With feature owners and marketing partners - this is solely my responsibility and the metric doesn’t help either of these types of colleagues. net promoter score (NPS) NPS is that whole “how likely would you recommend” set of questions, and it’s widely used. The problem is that it’s not actually a good metric by itself and most of the questions asked are leading. I prefer using alternative questions like, “In the last x time frame, have you considered switching products to our competitor? [Yes/No]”, which can help identify loyalty better than, “Would you recommend my product?” Another way this can be asked to be specific to your community is, “Have you had a community interaction in the last x time frame that made you think of leaving the community? [Yes/No]”. Including an open text box will allow users to tell you exactly where things are going wrong for them. The 1-10 scale is incredibly archaic and I dislike using it, the explicit binary answer gives you a clear picture of your promoters and detractors. ~ How I use this: Health of community reporting; primary KPI for success of brand recognition; success of a community program overall. ~ Where I won’t use this: Individual success - while we build brand recognition, this metric is representative of the product or community overall and not an individual. amplification rate This is essentially how much your followers are sharing your content specifically. Not to be confused with engagement rate, it shows how your reach is increasing. This is better to track than engagement rate because in community building you are trying to increase brand recognition in which this can correlate. Additionally, those who are the largest contributors to this metric can be considered your superfans you pull in. The type of data you have access to for a social platform determines if you can track this easily or not, but I think Orbit.love is one of the best ways to track this - I wish I was able to implement their product for Edge. AUTHOR'S NOTE, Nov 2025 orbit.love no longer seems to exist, which is pretty sad. It was acquired by Postman in April 2024, shortly after I started working for Nabu Casa, but now listed as part of JetRockets' portfolio. From what I can tell, this is just another open source victim of being gobbled up by the tech industry. 😔 ~ How I use this: With feature owners whose content I am helping amplify; health of community reporting; in presentations about brand-damaging content. ~ Where I won’t use this: With leadership audiences regularly - in cases where brand damage occurs, they need to understand how fast it spread, though. engagement Rate As I explained at the beginning of the post, engagement rate is just how much people engage with your content. Likes, shares, and comments all contribute to this and weigh the same against the metric. It’s useless by itself but good to look at in combination with sentiment as you watch the health of your community, and there are way too many ways to calculate this. This is why I prefer amplification rate over than engagement rate. ~ How I use this: With marketing partners during major industry events; health of community reporting to the team. ~ Where I won’t use this: With leadership audiences - they don’t look at the bigger picture of this number and often ignore when negative context is included. video views and video completion rate I am combining these two as they need to be together if you are going to use them. These are useful if you are creating video content for your community like fireside chats with your colleagues or walkthroughs for how to use your product. Views are calculated differently on each platform, so using views and completion time together shows a good picture of how well the content landed with your community. It’s also a great indication of how long you should be making your videos - optimizing the length of your videos helps with increasing completion rate. ~ How I use this: With marketing partners and feature owners whose content I am helping amplify; when planning out a content calendar. ~ Where I won’t use this: Health of community reporting - this just shows how well your content performs at that time; at the leadership level, they should not care how well your video performed. reach This is an easy metric to track, it’s simply how many people see your content and every tool out there can help show you it these days. You can keep an eye on the percentage who are followers and non-followers, however this metric really just shows how well your content performs combined with the size of your active following. An example of why this is bad to focus on: If your content goes viral in a negative way, you’re still getting that reach. ~ How I use this: With feature owners whose content I am helping amplify; with marketing partners during major industry events. ~ Where I won’t use this: With leadership audiences - they typically don’t grasp how reach works, and the conversations about its value tend to be circular. impressions Another confusing metric, impressions are how many times someone saw your content. An easy example is blog views - you can see how many unique people have visited your site and how many views it has had in total, and views will nearly always be higher than visits (unless you somehow maintain a 1:1 ratio). This means people keep coming back to what you’re talking about, which can be great to track, but without any other context this number doesn’t do much. ~ How I use this: 🫣 ~ Where I won’t use this: With anyone, I hate this metric. virality rate Now we’re just making up metrics, aren’t we? Gotta find something to justify your TikTok account? This is the number of shares (amplification) divided by the number of impressions. This is useless for community building and brand recognition - like reach, your virality rate means nothing without context. ~ How I use this: 🫣 ~ Where I won’t use this: With anyone, this is a vanity metric. return on investment metrics Click-through rate (CTR), conversion rate, cost-per-click (CPC), and cost per thousand impressions (CPM) are all almost exclusively social media metrics for paid content and what most leadership teams incorrectly consider community engagement metrics. I am against using these for community building because I think it’s gross justifying community content by how much it costs; content that is liked by the community but not “performing well” tends to be pushed aside for content that can prove it is earning the company money or returning value through these metrics. CTR can be used for organic (not paid) content to see how well you are encouraging people to go to the bigger picture and off the social platform you posted on, but that’s the extent of its usefulness - you can get that same traffic data from the website you are pointing to as the views and click sources. ~ How I use these: When pitching a new content series to be produced with marketing or teammates - I use them as goals based on historical ranges of the cost. ~ Where I won’t use these: Justifying 1:1 engagement with the community; health of community reporting - both of these should just roll into the salary of the employee as your ROI. The way I manage communities has me focus on its audience growth (with higher goals earlier in a community, lowering as the community grows) and sentiment shifts (diving into what is driving negative or positive sentiment over a specified percentage of volume, including share of voice). Everything else rolls into improving these really well. To show impact on the product as a feedback loop owner (as an engagement manager should be), I track the completion of feedback requests (including sentiment on the implementation of said feedback) and as much metadata about bugs escalated as possible (where it came from, link to other reports, the history of the item, and linking to bugs the engineers or feature owners own). I try to utilize CSAT and NPS as the bigger picture presented to leadership - a set of numbers that they can easily understand. Overall, the article about Measuring DevRel linked at the beginning of this word vomit is great advice for building up any community, not only developer-focused ones, since it digs into the specialty of the relationship owner and how to effectively do and measure each specialty. They give a really good picture as to what works and what doesn’t when it comes to community building. The author doesn’t agree with my take on NPS, but they also call out using a different question than the generic one is better than nothing. Some of my opinions here are hot takes and marketing partners I’ve told these to in the past were surprised at my opinion having been a long time community manager. Sure, you want to measure how well your content performs on social media, but ultimately how well your content performs doesn’t explain the macrosituation of your product - only how well your team can make high-performing social media content. -🧜‍♀️🦄]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Being an autistic woman in an industry that thinks it’s neurotypical - Part 2</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/archived/being-audhd-pt-2" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Being an autistic woman in an industry that thinks it’s neurotypical - Part 2" /><published>2023-04-20T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-04-20T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/archived/being%20audhd%20part%202</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/archived/being-audhd-pt-2"><![CDATA[<details>
<summary><b>AUTHOR NOTE</b></summary>
<i>This was originally posted on my WordPress blog, which I have deleted after migrating the blog's posts to this website in November 2025. Differences from the original are minimal and include: changing "neurodiverse" to "neurodivergent" across the post, adding a link to imgur with screenshots of a Xitter post no longer accessible to all, adding in paragraphs to reduce the wall of text, removing run-on sentences and their poor grammar, and in hindsight maybe I should have split out the mind map fangirling into another fucking post. 😅</i>
</details>
<p><br />
If you’re coming to this post, <b><a href="/archived/being-audhd-pt-1">please check out part 1 first</a></b> - all the experiences I laid out there taught me a lot about who I was and how it could further my career leading up to working on Edge, even without knowing that I’m autistic. I learned I’m extremely passionate about helping people and fostering close relationships, I earned specialization in escalation operations and know how to convince people to do what I am asking for, and I understand what it takes to run a variety of communities without being whatever toxic person I was when I lived in Colorado.<br />
<br />
I love data, am passionate about how to protect it, and wanted to use all of this to make meaningful changes within a product. I knew coming into the loop interviews for the Edge team what skills I could highlight, explain my weaknesses and how I work around them, and show how passionate I was about improving the lives of everyone. (Could I say passionate more? I need another synonym for that. 🤭)<br />
<br />
We’re up to December 2019 now. My role on the Microsoft Edge team allowed me to flourish, I was offered the chance to build the community how <b><em>I</em></b> wanted without restrictions that would render my superpowers useless. I <em>absolutely</em> give the credit to both my former manager and my assigned mentor. I connected with them really well - my manager was a huge supporter in me being the best and most authentic me, and my mentor kept me grounded in the face of corporate bullshit; I learned how to play the game at Microsoft very quickly.<br />
<br />
Oh, <em>what game</em>, you ask? It’s a popularity game, and if anyone tells you otherwise they are either blind or lying - if the people who are looking at rewards for the year know what you are doing and have done, you get rewarded for it, even if the impact isn’t in hard data. I know this because my role <em>consistently</em> didn’t have hard data to prove what I did, but everyone on the team knew me and valued what I offered to the broader team. If there’s one thing that I learned how to do on Edge, it was making myself <em>really</em> popular, very quickly, as the new communications owner and engagement specialist for the Edge Insiders and engineering team.<br />
<br />
I had no idea at the time that was thanks to my autism - <a href="https://www.autism.org/women-in-autism/#phenotype">autistic women tend to be way more social</a> than their male counterparts (<em>but also tend to get taken advantage of more</em>) and I often describe myself as an extroverted introvert (or occasionally an introverted extrovert 😉). Being the person everyone knew, and being someone that everyone loved (<em>their words, not mine, I have troubles seeing this, tHaNkS aUtIsM</em>), my impact was well beyond numbers, and I was rewarded year after year for how good I was for the team.<br />
<br />
Everyone talks about it at Microsoft but it’s a trip to experience first hand the firehose of becoming a Full Time Employee there the first time. It’s overwhelming but I thrive in hectic situations like this - I was learning something new, which is inherently <em>not boring</em>, and that is key for some autistic and people with ADHD to thrive in a role. About 8 months into the role, mid-2020, I felt the stress building and could tell my Lamictal wasn’t covering my anxiety anymore. My CBT wasn’t sticking, I was having panic attacks daily, crying from stress. I went back into therapy after my primary put me on Seroquel to reduce the new anxiety and the impact it was having on my sleep.<br />
<br />
This helped a lot, actually, but it wasn’t perfect. The pandemic and political climate wasn’t helping anything. I feel a lot of emotions, <em>all the time</em>, and when emotions are high from others I absorb it. It’s not fun, and 2020 was brutal for so many of us for so many reasons. My connection to emotions caused a lot of overwhelming bullshit to happen in my brain, combined with a great fear of the events unfolding in my country. The company encouraged people to take the time they needed to recover from whatever burnout they were feeling, but I don’t think a lot of people understand how much that time impacted the neurodivergent - stress reduces my ability to compensate and mask, causing a few issues both at work and home (and <a href="https://imgur.com/a/juv1QpT">currently causing me depression</a>).<br />
<br />
We go through our first re-org on the Edge team shortly after; the team’s Product head was moved to another Microsoft team in favor of the Engineering lead, moving Edge to run under him moving forward. This was a worry for me on the team because that Product head knew the importance of my role and carved out budget to ensure we got someone like me into the seat for the Edge Insiders. This re-org ended up giving my immediate team some engineers we desperately needed to help us achieve some of the projects we wanted to deliver to the Edge Insiders - I had some automation I needed to help track social better because Sprinklr was NOT the tool for what I did, we wanted to revamp the website, and we wanted to build up a version of the program to have Insiders earn rewards.<br />
<br />
<em>Well</em>, my team ended up butting heads with the feedback engineering manager often over priorities, and my last three Connects had something mentioning “working better with others” when it came to conflicting priorities (though my last one called out specifically that I am autistic and working on my CBT). I can be a bit stubborn when I’m challenged, my brain translates it as someone treating me as if I’m dumb and I <em>do not</em> react kindly when I feel like this. Thanks to emotional regulation issues, it’s much harder for me to wait to respond with more thought when this happens.<br />
<br />
It was rare that the Edge team made me feel this way, but there were times I felt this from partners who looked at my title and decided I was not technically inclined. I worked very hard on carefully choosing my words and <em>attempting</em> (improving with practice, to my credit) to reduce my emotional reaction in certain situations. I learned humility, humbleness, and the art of convincing others to prioritize my work within my first year being on the Edge team, in large part thanks to this re-org.<br />
<br />
A happy ending here: that engineering manager and I bonded pretty well over our shared frustrations in general, we ended up discovering that it wasn’t her who was causing the priority issues.<br />
<br />
Now it’s early 2021, I’ve suffered my second confirmed disc rupture (maybe actually the 4th or 5th looking back on my life), and it was now time to work with my medical team to get a breast reduction. To kick that off I received a diagnosis of <em>big ole titties</em> (<a href="https://www.merriam-webster.com/medical/macromastia">macromastia</a>); I had already lost 60 pounds (~27 kg), practiced <a href="https://www.healthline.com/nutrition/16-8-intermittent-fasting">a 16/8 intermittent fasting diet</a> for my diabetes, and active daily. I talk about this because this little thing (lol, <em>little</em>) <b>drastically</b> improved my self-confidence.<br />
<br />
Do you know what a cocky autistic person looks like? Of course you do, it’s what Elon Musk has been doing for the past couple years in the public eye. But confidence and I went a different route after my breast reduction; I was more humble thanks to my experience but comfortable in my skin and felt more like <em>me</em> than I ever have in my life. It’s important to note that I’ve wanted a breast reduction since I was 17; I have always had a much larger breast size than what should fit on my body, and the disc ruptures helped justify the surgery (which itself is a whole other story).<br />
<br />
At the end of August, 4 weeks post-surgery, I visited my mom while she was hosting my cousin - the same one who received a diagnosis of BPD a few years prior. This was an amazing bonding experience because I hadn’t seen this cousin since 2001. We talked a lot about mental health, childhood abuse, our oddly similar lives despite living across the country from each other, and the fact that my cousin was chasing an autism diagnosis. I took the <a href="https://embrace-autism.com/aq-10/">AQ-10</a>, a brief online version of the autism assessment, after they explained that the website was <a href="https://embrace-autism.com/about/">created by a neuropsychologist</a> who wanted easier access to this information available.<br />
<br />
I dug more into symptoms for autistic women, and <em>holy shit</em> - everything made sense. My <em>brother</em> is autistic, our <em>maternal grandfather</em> didn’t speak until he was 3 so we’re pretty sure he was autistic, and my cousin is my <em>mother’s</em> sister’s child - the dots were lining up. My <b>9/10</b> score was not too much of a shock after this research (NINE OUTTA TEN, BABY) and I used that score to help get an appointment with a neuropsychologist who specializes in diagnosing autistic women. I chatted with her about a month after reaching out on her website and got an appointment for testing in March 2022; the wait was worth it. This initial call made me realize things like me adjusting my seams on my clothing, pushing hair off of my skin, making sure my food didn’t touch, and pain tolerance were all related to sensory issues that came with my particular autism. <em>*more light bulb clicks*</em> Unfortunately, things at work quickly spiraled after this. Fun story time!<br />
<br />
In late 2021, Buy Now, Pay Later was introduced into the Edge browser with a <em>huge</em> amount of backlash. I helped the PM from the Shopping team draft the comms for the announcement to the Edge Insiders and went in with good faith that they knew what they were doing. I didn’t do much research into the impact of BNPL services on those who are neurodivergent and in low income areas, but I also hadn’t seen anything from the community that would have screamed “don’t do this shit”. I knew <em>of</em> the services, personally didn’t use them because I’m hyper-aware of not messing up my credit, and the PM was really good at giving me and my team all the benefits of the implementation. I came back from our first family vacation in Hawai’i to the largest PR disaster I’ve ever been involved with, which my <em>amazing</em> direct report shielded me from until I was back in office. (<em>Alex, I will never be able to repay you for that</em> 😭🙏)<br />
<br />
While I was spending my anniversary doing a coffee farm tour, the <a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/articles/introducing-buy-now-pay-later-in-microsoft-edge/m-p/2967030/">announcement post</a> went up and <b><em>everyone hated it</em></b>. It was an <em>immediate</em> explosion. Alex, bless her, tried her <em>fucking best</em> to get people to pay attention to the negative reactions and stressed that it was <em>not</em> normal in our community to get this kind of visceral reaction. Vendors at Microsoft often need an FTE backup even if they are more experienced than the FTEs they work with, so when I got back and caught up I had to actively step in to stress the kind of situation this was, drag in people’s managers, and petition leadership to listen. Everyone seemed to be furious it was being implemented.<br />
<br />
Buy Now, Pay Later payments disproportionally affect those with impulse control issues, those in low-income areas, as well impacting the credit of those who don’t make payments - <a href="https://www.consumerreports.org/shopping-retail/hidden-risks-of-buy-now-pay-later-plans-a7495893275/">up to 43%</a> of people using these services. When those points were brought up to people in leadership positions who could do something about it, nothing seemed to be enough to change course. We were told that it was the messaging that ruined the entire announcement, and that people just wanted something to be mad about or they simply hated new things.<br />
<br />
I mention this not to call anyone out, but so you understand the ridiculous amount of stress I went through; from high on life, thinking things were changing at Microsoft for the good, to absolutely wrecked within a couple weeks. <em>My job was to bring these angry voices to the people who would make a change, why weren’t the right people listening to the users? <b>What is the point of my job?</b></em> I had full on career existential crisis that continued until I was laid off over a year later.<br />
<br />
If you’re keeping track, I’ve just explained the course of 5 months from end of July to end of November 2021. The end of 2021 was such a roller coaster for me, I was praying that 2022 would be better. (We all know it wasn’t, cue more external stressors.)<br />
<br />
Alex left Microsoft in early 2022 and I legit did not know what I was going to do with myself for a bit; she kept me afloat, now I had to train someone new on top of still trying to find out what my purpose on the team was. I was drowning with negative social media posts and I just inherited the ticketed support service from a teammate who moved to another Edge group, putting more responsibilities on my shoulders that I also needed to balance. I suffered from a severe amount of burnout from November through March, largely due to absorbing all the negative emotions being thrown at me; burnout I don’t think I’m truly recovered from - I am scarred deep from that situation.<br />
<br />
March comes and I finally get to take my autism test. <b>I cannot understate how much this diagnosis changed everything for me.</b> I had an answer, one that <em>felt right</em>. It wasn’t just autism, though, no no! I got the surprise diagnosis of ADHD Inattentive type.<br />
<br />
Unexpected emotions came with this. I reflected on my life and realized all the times we unintentionally abused the autistic qualities out of me; where I was made fun of for being weird, my teachers calling me a motormouth but being part of gifted &amp; talented programs, making sure my food didn’t touch despite it all going to the same place, my lack of filter… everything made so much more sense, but I went through a period of mourning. I could have had a different life, I think, and it was heartbreaking experiencing this hindsight. If I hadn’t gone through what I have I would <em>not</em> be the person I am today.<br />
<br />
However, getting these diagnoses helped me find my center again; I had a new purpose in life and on the team - being successful with autism as an example of autism that breaks the mold. I decided to found and lead the Neurodiverse@Edge Employee Resource Group because there wasn’t a section on the team - I needed to create a space that would be truly safe for those of us ND-types who are not comfortable being open about our diagnoses, offer guidance to colleagues and managers on how to best support their ND peers and direct reports as allies, and be a support system for the group.<br />
<br />
In my diagnosis report, I learned a lot about myself and new tools that I could use to help with my deficiencies. I learned that my verbal comprehension is higher than my non-verbal. “Thinking out loud” is something I <em>have</em> to do if I want my brain to work faster; if I forget a word that I am trying to recall, I’ll start talking to myself about the connections to that word my brain keeps pulling, it’s super effective. I was introduced to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?app=desktop&amp;v=5nTuScU70As">mind mapping</a> - I thought I was organized before with my note taking and task organization I did in a daily planner, but this <em>blew. my. mind</em>.<br />
<br />
I dove deep into how to use this tool designed to help improve memory and found one program that would cover everything I needed, <a href="https://xmind.app/">Xmind</a>. It combines the functionality on a tablet I wanted for tactile input and the <em>~A E S T H E T I C~</em> customizations I crave - UX and UI are both incredibly important to me. To learn how to use a mind map, my first attempt was planning my in-law’s visit happening a month later. My <em>gods</em>, people, I caught onto how easy this was for my brain instantly - I could create buckets of categories that made sense to me, and as I added more information I could see other buckets that could be built, then easily moved the items that should be in that new category.<br />
<br />
I now use it for <em>everything</em> that needs coordination - company research for interviews, tracking what TV shows we’re watching on what platform (including what’s off season and cancelled), and work task tracking. I built up a template that I could duplicate every week to copy my daily tasks I was tracking and organize my work projects. I used to write my to-do lists and notes by hand but with the mind map I could just copy from the previous week, paste into the week I am organizing, easily drag and drop the list to the subsequent days, and create separate sheets within the same map to keep that week’s meeting notes separated from my tasks. I never lost a note, and I didn’t have to go digging through pages of a planner just to find something from weeks ago.<br />
<br />
I became a new force to reckon with; thanks to this productivity tool I was able to output more work than some of my peers while I was on a reduced work schedule due to my most recent disc rupture (5 or 6 now? I’ve lost count) from August - October 2022. I drove a Hackathon project to completion during this time, with our project winning 2nd place in our category. <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/missyquarry_auadhd-mindmapping-activity-7031682126634778624-I_wi/">I will word vomit to <em>anyone</em></a> the good word that is mind mapping and <em>especially</em> stress that neurodivergent people who suffer from working memory and executive function issues adopt this form of organization.<br />
<br />
I also adopted the use of focus features in Apple products like the background noise using the stream setting. Music <em>can</em> be used for background noise, but it’s more often than not a distraction for those with ADHD, pulling you into the lyrics of a good song and away from the work you were doing. Noise-cancelling headphones are <b>a must have</b> for someone with sensory issues, something I didn’t realize I had until working with my son’s behavioral specialists and the <em>click</em> of the light bulb where he got his from.<br />
<br />
My specific audio sensory issue is that I can focus on anything I want to, often <em>when I don’t</em> want to, with my ears picking up nearly everything around me. I can focus on specific sounds even in a crowded room; having noise-cancelling headphones with the stream playing helps me focus without the loudness of my environment. Monday mornings I blocked out 45-60 minutes first thing in my work hours so that I could ensure my weekly mind map was created. To help with my memory recollection, I started blocking out “focus” time for 15 minutes after meetings to organize tasks and projects on my mind map before moving on to the next thing.<br />
<br />
Not once did I get pushback when I politely asked whoever set up a meeting with me to move it 15 minutes forward to accommodate for those breaks; in fact, I often get back a “holy crap, that’s a great idea, I should start that!” (<a href="https://www.linkedin.com/feed/update/urn:li:activity:7047620126023503872/">You really should start</a>, regardless.) I started working in chunks of time, used away messages/statuses on Teams to prompt people to leave me detailed notes when they want information from me (<em>No Hello, please!</em>), and drew a thicker work/life balance line to support my unique capabilities.<br />
<br />
Picking all of these tools up meant I also had to advocate more for myself. I sent an email to my fellow org PMs detailing my diagnosis and what I was doing to shift how I worked moving forward. The reaction to that email was nothing but support and callouts that what I am doing will work for even the neurotypical! It took me about a month to fold all of these changes into my processes, mind mapping has a <em>super heavy lift</em> up front, and I spent a lot of time setting up inbox zero for more organization. These all helped me be more successful during my last year on the Edge team, <b>all because I got that diagnosis of autism</b>. Whichever company hires me next is getting a high performer who knows her limits and superpowers, along with the organizational skills of a robot.<br />
<br />
It’s ridiculous, this world was built for average and so many of us <em>just don’t fit that</em>. I <em>literally</em> cannot function like the average person and expecting the neurodivergent to conform has caused us severe stress by essentially <a href="https://childmind.org/article/controversy-around-applied-behavior-analysis/">abusing out what makes us unique</a>. That’s honestly my whole point of this post series, to bring to light how neurodivergent people can experience life, particularly if they don’t know they <em>are</em> ND and/or they don’t advocate for themselves. <a href="https://hbr.org/2017/05/neurodiversity-as-a-competitive-advantage">Being neurodivergent is an advantage</a> in the tech industry, “… <a href="https://www.spartaglobal.com/learn-and-media/equaltech-report-2023-neurodiversity-in-tech/">autistic people in the right environment can be 140% more productive than their peers</a>”. Yes, I <em>can</em> prove that I am that productive. Yet we still have “personality” tests barring autistic people and those with ADHD from qualifying, force people through stressful assignments just for an interview, and <em>I can’t prove it but</em> I sometimes feel that when I self-describe that have a disability I am immediately tossed aside (<em><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/deborah-lalush_tech-design-activity-7048692879069753344-SE25">I’m not the only autistic person noticing this pattern</a>, either</em>).<br />
<br />
Despite many tech companies actively sourcing autistic talent, hiring that talent is still <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20211019144046/https://www.mcgregor-boyall.com/our-thinking-library/2021/02/neurodiversity-in-the-tech-industry/243">a huge fucking problem</a>, especially when you can’t say what disability you have when you self-describe (and I’m aware of <em>so many</em> ND peeps who have been let go from tech companies this year 😔). A lot of internal support or programs are nothing but lip service, touting a space of psychological safety while rewarding those who actively make teams toxic and unsafe by promoting them into higher positions of power.<br />
<br />
Leadership teams expect the work needed for cultural improvements to be from the ground up when it should be a collaborative effort driven by leadership, top down, <em>but also</em> ground up from the individual contributors and their managers. I’m a supporter of burning down the entire system we have, so I’m sure it won’t surprise you that I believe to properly be inclusive and diverse we need to get rid of everyone in a C-Suite position at most tech companies and redo it all.<br />
<br />
I didn’t want to end this on a rant, but that’s how things go with me, I suppose. I’m sad that I didn’t who I really am until my mid-30s, I probably wouldn’t have ruined so many friendships or burned bridges at places of employment. I want my story to be out there so that maybe I will be that “Halsey moment” to someone that she was for me - showing that you can be successful regardless of having a disability that affects your executive function. And hopefully you learned something new about me - “never would have guessed” is something I am told often, and to that I say, “Yeah, <a href="https://www.autism.org.uk/advice-and-guidance/professional-practice/autistic-masking">that’s unconsciously intentional</a>.”<br />
<br />
-🧜‍♀️🦄</p>]]></content><author><name>the cyborg</name></author><category term="archived" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[AUTHOR NOTE This was originally posted on my WordPress blog, which I have deleted after migrating the blog's posts to this website in November 2025. Differences from the original are minimal and include: changing "neurodiverse" to "neurodivergent" across the post, adding a link to imgur with screenshots of a Xitter post no longer accessible to all, adding in paragraphs to reduce the wall of text, removing run-on sentences and their poor grammar, and in hindsight maybe I should have split out the mind map fangirling into another fucking post. 😅 If you’re coming to this post, please check out part 1 first - all the experiences I laid out there taught me a lot about who I was and how it could further my career leading up to working on Edge, even without knowing that I’m autistic. I learned I’m extremely passionate about helping people and fostering close relationships, I earned specialization in escalation operations and know how to convince people to do what I am asking for, and I understand what it takes to run a variety of communities without being whatever toxic person I was when I lived in Colorado. I love data, am passionate about how to protect it, and wanted to use all of this to make meaningful changes within a product. I knew coming into the loop interviews for the Edge team what skills I could highlight, explain my weaknesses and how I work around them, and show how passionate I was about improving the lives of everyone. (Could I say passionate more? I need another synonym for that. 🤭) We’re up to December 2019 now. My role on the Microsoft Edge team allowed me to flourish, I was offered the chance to build the community how I wanted without restrictions that would render my superpowers useless. I absolutely give the credit to both my former manager and my assigned mentor. I connected with them really well - my manager was a huge supporter in me being the best and most authentic me, and my mentor kept me grounded in the face of corporate bullshit; I learned how to play the game at Microsoft very quickly. Oh, what game, you ask? It’s a popularity game, and if anyone tells you otherwise they are either blind or lying - if the people who are looking at rewards for the year know what you are doing and have done, you get rewarded for it, even if the impact isn’t in hard data. I know this because my role consistently didn’t have hard data to prove what I did, but everyone on the team knew me and valued what I offered to the broader team. If there’s one thing that I learned how to do on Edge, it was making myself really popular, very quickly, as the new communications owner and engagement specialist for the Edge Insiders and engineering team. I had no idea at the time that was thanks to my autism - autistic women tend to be way more social than their male counterparts (but also tend to get taken advantage of more) and I often describe myself as an extroverted introvert (or occasionally an introverted extrovert 😉). Being the person everyone knew, and being someone that everyone loved (their words, not mine, I have troubles seeing this, tHaNkS aUtIsM), my impact was well beyond numbers, and I was rewarded year after year for how good I was for the team. Everyone talks about it at Microsoft but it’s a trip to experience first hand the firehose of becoming a Full Time Employee there the first time. It’s overwhelming but I thrive in hectic situations like this - I was learning something new, which is inherently not boring, and that is key for some autistic and people with ADHD to thrive in a role. About 8 months into the role, mid-2020, I felt the stress building and could tell my Lamictal wasn’t covering my anxiety anymore. My CBT wasn’t sticking, I was having panic attacks daily, crying from stress. I went back into therapy after my primary put me on Seroquel to reduce the new anxiety and the impact it was having on my sleep. This helped a lot, actually, but it wasn’t perfect. The pandemic and political climate wasn’t helping anything. I feel a lot of emotions, all the time, and when emotions are high from others I absorb it. It’s not fun, and 2020 was brutal for so many of us for so many reasons. My connection to emotions caused a lot of overwhelming bullshit to happen in my brain, combined with a great fear of the events unfolding in my country. The company encouraged people to take the time they needed to recover from whatever burnout they were feeling, but I don’t think a lot of people understand how much that time impacted the neurodivergent - stress reduces my ability to compensate and mask, causing a few issues both at work and home (and currently causing me depression). We go through our first re-org on the Edge team shortly after; the team’s Product head was moved to another Microsoft team in favor of the Engineering lead, moving Edge to run under him moving forward. This was a worry for me on the team because that Product head knew the importance of my role and carved out budget to ensure we got someone like me into the seat for the Edge Insiders. This re-org ended up giving my immediate team some engineers we desperately needed to help us achieve some of the projects we wanted to deliver to the Edge Insiders - I had some automation I needed to help track social better because Sprinklr was NOT the tool for what I did, we wanted to revamp the website, and we wanted to build up a version of the program to have Insiders earn rewards. Well, my team ended up butting heads with the feedback engineering manager often over priorities, and my last three Connects had something mentioning “working better with others” when it came to conflicting priorities (though my last one called out specifically that I am autistic and working on my CBT). I can be a bit stubborn when I’m challenged, my brain translates it as someone treating me as if I’m dumb and I do not react kindly when I feel like this. Thanks to emotional regulation issues, it’s much harder for me to wait to respond with more thought when this happens. It was rare that the Edge team made me feel this way, but there were times I felt this from partners who looked at my title and decided I was not technically inclined. I worked very hard on carefully choosing my words and attempting (improving with practice, to my credit) to reduce my emotional reaction in certain situations. I learned humility, humbleness, and the art of convincing others to prioritize my work within my first year being on the Edge team, in large part thanks to this re-org. A happy ending here: that engineering manager and I bonded pretty well over our shared frustrations in general, we ended up discovering that it wasn’t her who was causing the priority issues. Now it’s early 2021, I’ve suffered my second confirmed disc rupture (maybe actually the 4th or 5th looking back on my life), and it was now time to work with my medical team to get a breast reduction. To kick that off I received a diagnosis of big ole titties (macromastia); I had already lost 60 pounds (~27 kg), practiced a 16/8 intermittent fasting diet for my diabetes, and active daily. I talk about this because this little thing (lol, little) drastically improved my self-confidence. Do you know what a cocky autistic person looks like? Of course you do, it’s what Elon Musk has been doing for the past couple years in the public eye. But confidence and I went a different route after my breast reduction; I was more humble thanks to my experience but comfortable in my skin and felt more like me than I ever have in my life. It’s important to note that I’ve wanted a breast reduction since I was 17; I have always had a much larger breast size than what should fit on my body, and the disc ruptures helped justify the surgery (which itself is a whole other story). At the end of August, 4 weeks post-surgery, I visited my mom while she was hosting my cousin - the same one who received a diagnosis of BPD a few years prior. This was an amazing bonding experience because I hadn’t seen this cousin since 2001. We talked a lot about mental health, childhood abuse, our oddly similar lives despite living across the country from each other, and the fact that my cousin was chasing an autism diagnosis. I took the AQ-10, a brief online version of the autism assessment, after they explained that the website was created by a neuropsychologist who wanted easier access to this information available. I dug more into symptoms for autistic women, and holy shit - everything made sense. My brother is autistic, our maternal grandfather didn’t speak until he was 3 so we’re pretty sure he was autistic, and my cousin is my mother’s sister’s child - the dots were lining up. My 9/10 score was not too much of a shock after this research (NINE OUTTA TEN, BABY) and I used that score to help get an appointment with a neuropsychologist who specializes in diagnosing autistic women. I chatted with her about a month after reaching out on her website and got an appointment for testing in March 2022; the wait was worth it. This initial call made me realize things like me adjusting my seams on my clothing, pushing hair off of my skin, making sure my food didn’t touch, and pain tolerance were all related to sensory issues that came with my particular autism. *more light bulb clicks* Unfortunately, things at work quickly spiraled after this. Fun story time! In late 2021, Buy Now, Pay Later was introduced into the Edge browser with a huge amount of backlash. I helped the PM from the Shopping team draft the comms for the announcement to the Edge Insiders and went in with good faith that they knew what they were doing. I didn’t do much research into the impact of BNPL services on those who are neurodivergent and in low income areas, but I also hadn’t seen anything from the community that would have screamed “don’t do this shit”. I knew of the services, personally didn’t use them because I’m hyper-aware of not messing up my credit, and the PM was really good at giving me and my team all the benefits of the implementation. I came back from our first family vacation in Hawai’i to the largest PR disaster I’ve ever been involved with, which my amazing direct report shielded me from until I was back in office. (Alex, I will never be able to repay you for that 😭🙏) While I was spending my anniversary doing a coffee farm tour, the announcement post went up and everyone hated it. It was an immediate explosion. Alex, bless her, tried her fucking best to get people to pay attention to the negative reactions and stressed that it was not normal in our community to get this kind of visceral reaction. Vendors at Microsoft often need an FTE backup even if they are more experienced than the FTEs they work with, so when I got back and caught up I had to actively step in to stress the kind of situation this was, drag in people’s managers, and petition leadership to listen. Everyone seemed to be furious it was being implemented. Buy Now, Pay Later payments disproportionally affect those with impulse control issues, those in low-income areas, as well impacting the credit of those who don’t make payments - up to 43% of people using these services. When those points were brought up to people in leadership positions who could do something about it, nothing seemed to be enough to change course. We were told that it was the messaging that ruined the entire announcement, and that people just wanted something to be mad about or they simply hated new things. I mention this not to call anyone out, but so you understand the ridiculous amount of stress I went through; from high on life, thinking things were changing at Microsoft for the good, to absolutely wrecked within a couple weeks. My job was to bring these angry voices to the people who would make a change, why weren’t the right people listening to the users? What is the point of my job? I had full on career existential crisis that continued until I was laid off over a year later. If you’re keeping track, I’ve just explained the course of 5 months from end of July to end of November 2021. The end of 2021 was such a roller coaster for me, I was praying that 2022 would be better. (We all know it wasn’t, cue more external stressors.) Alex left Microsoft in early 2022 and I legit did not know what I was going to do with myself for a bit; she kept me afloat, now I had to train someone new on top of still trying to find out what my purpose on the team was. I was drowning with negative social media posts and I just inherited the ticketed support service from a teammate who moved to another Edge group, putting more responsibilities on my shoulders that I also needed to balance. I suffered from a severe amount of burnout from November through March, largely due to absorbing all the negative emotions being thrown at me; burnout I don’t think I’m truly recovered from - I am scarred deep from that situation. March comes and I finally get to take my autism test. I cannot understate how much this diagnosis changed everything for me. I had an answer, one that felt right. It wasn’t just autism, though, no no! I got the surprise diagnosis of ADHD Inattentive type. Unexpected emotions came with this. I reflected on my life and realized all the times we unintentionally abused the autistic qualities out of me; where I was made fun of for being weird, my teachers calling me a motormouth but being part of gifted &amp; talented programs, making sure my food didn’t touch despite it all going to the same place, my lack of filter… everything made so much more sense, but I went through a period of mourning. I could have had a different life, I think, and it was heartbreaking experiencing this hindsight. If I hadn’t gone through what I have I would not be the person I am today. However, getting these diagnoses helped me find my center again; I had a new purpose in life and on the team - being successful with autism as an example of autism that breaks the mold. I decided to found and lead the Neurodiverse@Edge Employee Resource Group because there wasn’t a section on the team - I needed to create a space that would be truly safe for those of us ND-types who are not comfortable being open about our diagnoses, offer guidance to colleagues and managers on how to best support their ND peers and direct reports as allies, and be a support system for the group. In my diagnosis report, I learned a lot about myself and new tools that I could use to help with my deficiencies. I learned that my verbal comprehension is higher than my non-verbal. “Thinking out loud” is something I have to do if I want my brain to work faster; if I forget a word that I am trying to recall, I’ll start talking to myself about the connections to that word my brain keeps pulling, it’s super effective. I was introduced to mind mapping - I thought I was organized before with my note taking and task organization I did in a daily planner, but this blew. my. mind. I dove deep into how to use this tool designed to help improve memory and found one program that would cover everything I needed, Xmind. It combines the functionality on a tablet I wanted for tactile input and the ~A E S T H E T I C~ customizations I crave - UX and UI are both incredibly important to me. To learn how to use a mind map, my first attempt was planning my in-law’s visit happening a month later. My gods, people, I caught onto how easy this was for my brain instantly - I could create buckets of categories that made sense to me, and as I added more information I could see other buckets that could be built, then easily moved the items that should be in that new category. I now use it for everything that needs coordination - company research for interviews, tracking what TV shows we’re watching on what platform (including what’s off season and cancelled), and work task tracking. I built up a template that I could duplicate every week to copy my daily tasks I was tracking and organize my work projects. I used to write my to-do lists and notes by hand but with the mind map I could just copy from the previous week, paste into the week I am organizing, easily drag and drop the list to the subsequent days, and create separate sheets within the same map to keep that week’s meeting notes separated from my tasks. I never lost a note, and I didn’t have to go digging through pages of a planner just to find something from weeks ago. I became a new force to reckon with; thanks to this productivity tool I was able to output more work than some of my peers while I was on a reduced work schedule due to my most recent disc rupture (5 or 6 now? I’ve lost count) from August - October 2022. I drove a Hackathon project to completion during this time, with our project winning 2nd place in our category. I will word vomit to anyone the good word that is mind mapping and especially stress that neurodivergent people who suffer from working memory and executive function issues adopt this form of organization. I also adopted the use of focus features in Apple products like the background noise using the stream setting. Music can be used for background noise, but it’s more often than not a distraction for those with ADHD, pulling you into the lyrics of a good song and away from the work you were doing. Noise-cancelling headphones are a must have for someone with sensory issues, something I didn’t realize I had until working with my son’s behavioral specialists and the click of the light bulb where he got his from. My specific audio sensory issue is that I can focus on anything I want to, often when I don’t want to, with my ears picking up nearly everything around me. I can focus on specific sounds even in a crowded room; having noise-cancelling headphones with the stream playing helps me focus without the loudness of my environment. Monday mornings I blocked out 45-60 minutes first thing in my work hours so that I could ensure my weekly mind map was created. To help with my memory recollection, I started blocking out “focus” time for 15 minutes after meetings to organize tasks and projects on my mind map before moving on to the next thing. Not once did I get pushback when I politely asked whoever set up a meeting with me to move it 15 minutes forward to accommodate for those breaks; in fact, I often get back a “holy crap, that’s a great idea, I should start that!” (You really should start, regardless.) I started working in chunks of time, used away messages/statuses on Teams to prompt people to leave me detailed notes when they want information from me (No Hello, please!), and drew a thicker work/life balance line to support my unique capabilities. Picking all of these tools up meant I also had to advocate more for myself. I sent an email to my fellow org PMs detailing my diagnosis and what I was doing to shift how I worked moving forward. The reaction to that email was nothing but support and callouts that what I am doing will work for even the neurotypical! It took me about a month to fold all of these changes into my processes, mind mapping has a super heavy lift up front, and I spent a lot of time setting up inbox zero for more organization. These all helped me be more successful during my last year on the Edge team, all because I got that diagnosis of autism. Whichever company hires me next is getting a high performer who knows her limits and superpowers, along with the organizational skills of a robot. It’s ridiculous, this world was built for average and so many of us just don’t fit that. I literally cannot function like the average person and expecting the neurodivergent to conform has caused us severe stress by essentially abusing out what makes us unique. That’s honestly my whole point of this post series, to bring to light how neurodivergent people can experience life, particularly if they don’t know they are ND and/or they don’t advocate for themselves. Being neurodivergent is an advantage in the tech industry, “… autistic people in the right environment can be 140% more productive than their peers”. Yes, I can prove that I am that productive. Yet we still have “personality” tests barring autistic people and those with ADHD from qualifying, force people through stressful assignments just for an interview, and I can’t prove it but I sometimes feel that when I self-describe that have a disability I am immediately tossed aside (I’m not the only autistic person noticing this pattern, either). Despite many tech companies actively sourcing autistic talent, hiring that talent is still a huge fucking problem, especially when you can’t say what disability you have when you self-describe (and I’m aware of so many ND peeps who have been let go from tech companies this year 😔). A lot of internal support or programs are nothing but lip service, touting a space of psychological safety while rewarding those who actively make teams toxic and unsafe by promoting them into higher positions of power. Leadership teams expect the work needed for cultural improvements to be from the ground up when it should be a collaborative effort driven by leadership, top down, but also ground up from the individual contributors and their managers. I’m a supporter of burning down the entire system we have, so I’m sure it won’t surprise you that I believe to properly be inclusive and diverse we need to get rid of everyone in a C-Suite position at most tech companies and redo it all. I didn’t want to end this on a rant, but that’s how things go with me, I suppose. I’m sad that I didn’t who I really am until my mid-30s, I probably wouldn’t have ruined so many friendships or burned bridges at places of employment. I want my story to be out there so that maybe I will be that “Halsey moment” to someone that she was for me - showing that you can be successful regardless of having a disability that affects your executive function. And hopefully you learned something new about me - “never would have guessed” is something I am told often, and to that I say, “Yeah, that’s unconsciously intentional.” -🧜‍♀️🦄]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Being an autistic woman in an industry that thinks it’s neurotypical - Part 1</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/archived/being-audhd-pt-1" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Being an autistic woman in an industry that thinks it’s neurotypical - Part 1" /><published>2023-04-11T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-04-11T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/archived/being%20audhd%20part%201</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/archived/being-audhd-pt-1"><![CDATA[<details>
<summary><b>AUTHOR NOTE</b></summary>
<i>This was originally posted on my WordPress blog, which I have deleted after migrating the blog's posts to this website in November 2025. Differences from the original are minimal and include: rephrasing "neurodiverse" as "neurodivergent" throughout the post, changed a few things to make more grammatical sense, and created more paraphraphs to reduce the wall of text feel.</i>
</details>
<p><br />
It’s April, which means it’s Autism Acceptance Month! The tech industry believes it to be a space where average people can make a difference in the world, but more often than not these high performing employees are neurodivergent in a neurotypical world.<br />
<br />
<b>Obligatory note: When you meet someone with autism, you have met <em>one person</em> with autism.</b> We are all unique individuals with a variety of superpowers (some don’t even like that term!), and my experiences are not reflective of the overall neurodivergent community. Are you on the neurodivergent spectrum or think you may be? I’d love to hear your experiences! I’m 100% down to help you navigate this world and how you can be the best you possible. 🥰<br />
<br />
Before I begin, I implore you, <b><em>do not</em></b> support Autism Speaks, spread the puzzle piece, or <em>speak for</em> autistic people. Make room for us to have our own voices this month - we don’t need your help to be vocal, but we do need your help in elevating our experiences and needs, so take some time this month to make sure you spread the right kind of voices.<br />
<br />
I’m gonna start this with: Do you realize what all I <b>need</b> to do to ensure my anxiety is under control in this ridiculous world? Unless I’ve told you directly, probably not. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conditions_comorbid_to_autism_spectrum_disorders">Anxiety is often a comorbidity</a> of both autism and ADHD, and it’s quite common to be treated for anxiety when you have either of those. I was diagnosed with bipolar II and severe general anxiety in 2007 and I need 1) an anticonvulsant used as a mood stabilizer to help with my big swings, 2) a traditional mood stabilizer to help sedate me, improve my sleep quality, and keep my anxiety down, 3) an as-needed anti-anxiety medication when things get way fucked, and 4) I constantly use <a href="https://www.apa.org/ptsd-guideline/patients-and-families/cognitive-behavioral">Cognitive Behavior Therapy</a> techniques to bring me back to my center.<br />
<br />
I’m convinced a large part of this is needed because people value “normal” over “uniqueness” thanks to capitalism, and it’s a huge reason why I would love to just go live on an island tending a community farm far away from tech (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_V17JN76uxc">Ancient Dreams in a Modern Land</a> is a mood for this). The tech industry is <em>full</em> of neurodivergent people, yet those in charge are in general Boomer age (<em>or have Boomer ideologies</em>), think people who get mental health help are “weak” or “snowflakes”, and often tell their employees to “deal with it”. This leads to excessive stress which leads to over-medication which leads to a lot of people feeling like they are not valued as a human.<br />
<br />
Now that’s out of the way, this post is <em>part 1</em> of two about my career experiences before and after my autism diagnosis, focusing on before I was an FTE at Microsoft (part 2 will be about my time on Edge and after my diagnosis). <a href="https://psychcentral.com/autism/levels-of-autism">Autism Level 1</a> was originally called Asperger’s, but <em>we don’t talk about him anymore</em> (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hans_Asperger">bad Nazi doing bad experiments</a>, you should avoid using the term ‘Aspie’ for this reason).<br />
<br /></p>
<details>
<summary><b>AUTHOR'S NOTE, Nov 2025</b></summary>
<i>Past Missy lied, there are actually 3 parts to this series, the third is in drafts as of publishing this.</i>
</details>
<p><br />
After I was first diagnosed with bipolar II, I learned that working overnights is <em>terrible</em> for bipolar brains. Who’s got two thumbs and was working overnights at Walmart at the time? <em>This bitch</em>. We lived in Colorado (where I was raised) and before this diagnosis I already did a ton of damage to my unfocused career.<br />
<br />
I exploded at my first job, a bowling alley, because I asked one of my coworkers for a pretzel and cheese from the food counter and he sent back a <em>Slimfast</em>. As I stormed out, I chucked the can at his head (<em>I missed, unfortunately</em>), stopped by the Manager’s office to take off my work shirt and throw it with my badge at the Assistant Manager’s face, then I walked out.<br />
<br />
I worked at a Denny’s briefly overnights where I was accused of taking meth in the bathroom because I am…uh…too cheery? Wish I was joking about that one. 😑<br />
<br />
While I was in trade school to be a mechanic, I worked at a KFC/A&amp;W with a school mate. I hated smelling like chicken all the time so I quit to be a nanny for my old neighbor and a friend of hers. I guess my roommate didn’t like some of that and while I was at my mom’s one extended weekend, that roommate packed all her shit up leaving behind a note and a few ceramic pigs that told me how horrible I was; said pigs were violently introduced to the wall when I read the letter. (To this day I still don’t know what I did to deserve that but <em>her</em> credit got fucked because she didn’t break the lease properly. 😂)<br />
<br />
I worked in customer service for Microcenter where I kept getting horrible anxiety every day I had to work so I sabotaged that by just…not showing up anymore.<br />
<br />
All this was within 4 years, 2003-2007, and these are <em>only the job things</em> - I burned a lot more bridges with friends and my husband (then boyfriend) during this time, too.<br />
<br />
After my bipolar diagnosis, I moved to the day shift at the customer service counter for Walmart. I started medications to control the mood swings, and went through so many before I found the “right” one - I ended up on depakote for a couple years. When we decided we wanted to leave Colorado for the Pacific Northwest in 2008, we moved in with my mother-in-law so that we could save up money for the move across the US.<br />
<br />
<em>spoiler</em>: we didn’t save anything because we both have ADHD and planning ahead was not a specialty of ours. 😅<br />
<br />
But during that time I worked with my mother-in-law as a virtual assistant helping with content creation and editing videos for her clients, and I’m <em>pretty sure</em> I stopped taking my medication and focused solely on CBT. Genuinely can’t recall anymore.<br />
<br />
In 2010, we decided I needed a “real” job (<em>lol</em>) and my husband saw that a company he used to work for, iBeta, wanted some software testers. He convinced me to apply by telling me, “It’s your favorite thing, pointing out other people’s flaws!” That line actually worked in the interview, and for a year I worked as a software and hardware tester for SMART boards and monitors. To this day, this is <em>my favorite</em> way that explains how I got into tech. I continued to have anxiety issues that would make me call out of work more often than I probably should have; my manager there told me that I would be significantly better at my job if I put more effort into making sure I was around. I didn’t know at the time that I should have been advocating for my anxiety this early in my career, and I wish I did.<br />
<br />
It’s 2011 now and we finally had enough to move up to Oregon - except we only <em>thought</em> we did and that entire situation was a mess, too. 😬 My first job in Portland, Oregon I lasted only 3 months doing iPhone and iPad phone support. I’m pretty sure that I ruptured a disc because I could not sit for extended periods or in certain ways, but we had no health insurance (<em>because call centers treat their employees like chicken</em>) so I had no way to find out what was really happening. Since I couldn’t take any time off to recover (<em>because how dare call center employees get hurt or sick</em>), I was unfortunately let go.<br />
<br />
Instead of getting another corporate job, I started building up my own business making jewelry by crowdsourcing funds to buy tools. I taught myself how to solder, learned I could make things in 3D form really well (<em>I always thought I wasn’t artistic</em>), and managed to get a little money out of it. But…me not finding a stable job really hurt us. The cost of that was needing to separate from my husband, give up two of our three cats, and move in with my parents in southern Oregon. My husband still had a job - the one that would eventually change our lives - so he stayed up in Portland by himself working as phone support for Xbox.<br />
<br />
When I moved back to Portland mid-2012, I ended up getting a job with the husband unit doing phone support for Xbox. The very first phone call I took during training my trainer pulled my husband aside and said, “She sounds like she’s done this her whole life, she’s a <em>natural</em>.” Inside, I was terrified, felt like my voice was wavering, and got an adrenaline rush that gave me a headache and the shakes because of my anxiety. It’s amazing what masking your entire life lets you do.<br />
<br />
Like I noted in <a href="/archived/art-of-empathy">my post about empathy</a>, I was <em>really</em> good at what I did for Xbox, especially once I got confidence in my skills. I was a networking specialist, only one of two women who were on that team. Would you believe that I could easily take my troubleshooting skills from being a trained diesel engine and heavy duty transmission mechanic and fold it into networking? This role taught me how technically-inclined I truly am; I could do in-depth, technical conversations with users and find answers outside of the troubleshooting built into the support tool we used.<br />
<br />
As support agents, we helped scale up a new call center building in Wilsonville, Oregon and during that transition an opening on the Games for Windows Live team became available. This was a highly desired role within in the call center - they had pretty low call volume and most of the time the answer was “turn off your antivirus”. I scored that seat (the only woman agent on the team with a woman manager) the same time my husband got selected to go up to Redmond and help the Xbox supportability PMs build up the networking section and troubleshooting flows for the original Xbox One.<br />
<br />
I am <em>still</em> shocked at how well I did at the call center for someone who hates talking to people, but this role is the first one I can see the excessive amount of masking and compensation I was doing to get through things. For example, I got back onto an as-needed anti-anxiety medication so that I wouldn’t sabotage yet another job (lorazepam), found a group of people who were similar to me, and made some new life-long friends.<br />
<br />
My husband ended up impressing one of the FTEs for Xbox Community Support, and that man (hi, James, if you ever read this!) worked hard to get both of us up to the Seattle area and working on his team. I also mentioned in my empathy post that I was told by my first lead on Xbox, “You talk to <em>problems</em>, not <em>people</em>.” I did not realize that my “learning” empathy and how to engage in text form as a company representative was a form of autistic compensating. I have always been known for not having a filter from my brain to my mouth, not thinking how people would react to a) <em>what</em> I was saying and b) <em>how</em> I was saying it. Tbh, sometimes I still don’t give a shit - sometimes you need that blunt slap in the face because a lot of people won’t do it. I am that friend who will give it to you straight. <em>Shit, I lost track of where I was going with this.</em><br />
<br />
Oh, <em>right</em>, how I got unfairly fired from Xbox Community Support due to my lack of filter, directly related to my autism. 🙂‍↕️<br />
<br />
I started as a support forums agent, helped launch the Xbox Support handle on Reddit, and moved into a Community Manager role for the Xbox Ambassadors. A beloved staff member of the Ambassadors, I had a rough day and snapped at a community member for being a shithead in Discord. I wasn’t <em>bad</em> about it, he was ranting about something he was upset with, and I said, “Be constructive or be quiet.” I’ll be the first to say I recognize I could have done better there. Very shortly after the exchange this community member left the Discord server. He was <em>well known</em> for this when he would throw a fit, so it wasn’t anything new, and I honestly didn’t even notice because he was still talking to me in private messages.<br />
<br />
But someone on the team decided that this course of events meant I pushed him out of the community and made it an unsafe space for the rest. <b><em>Except it wasn’t my interaction with him that made him leave</em></b>. No one involved with my firing asked the community member what happened, no one talked to other community members like the volunteer moderators who were there, no one talked to <em>me</em> about the situation. About a week after the incident, I get pulled into a room and told that because he left the server after that interaction I was being fired. The member this was centered around tried to petition the team to listen, but they weren’t having it. Mentions of me in the Discord server were removed, a petition on the forums was ignored, my ex-colleagues mostly shunned me. To this day, I (and several others) fully believe that one “bad” interaction after 4 years <em>did not</em> warrant me getting fired.<br />
<br />
And that’s how I accidentally sabotaged a job <em>I fucking loved</em> by not having a filter thanks to autism, and man if I had known then what I know now things might have gone way different. (Like, <em>probably not getting fired in the first place</em>, for example.)<br />
<br />
During my time on XCS from 2014-2018, I discovered Halsey (<em>who didn’t at this point, amirite</em>?), learned that she’s openly bipolar and was stoked to see someone like me sing about their experiences. Most of her Badlands album is just a call to my soul, but Gasoline, Castle, and Control are 3 songs that I relate to the most. My cousin was re-diagnosed from bipolar to <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/borderline-personality-disorder/symptoms-causes/syc-20370237">borderline personality disorder</a> closer to the end of this period, maybe 2017 or 2018.<br />
<br />
It got me re-evaluating my diagnosis of bipolar as something a little more so I went to a psychologist to get on mood stabilizing medication again and talk more about BPD. I was put on Lamictal then for my bipolar, told that we should focus on the symptoms and not the diagnosis (<em>fine</em> 🙄), and then released once the Lamictal controlled my swings and anxiety. Despite the lack of support for a new diagnosis from this psych, I will <em><b>forever</b></em> state that Lamictal saved my life, my relationships, and my career.<br />
<br />
The role I had after XCS taught me that I <em>love</em> machine learning. As a content analyst for a conversational AI, I learned how to speak to a machine and realized that coding is quite literally simply learning another language - it’s just for machines, and my analytical brain <em>easily</em> understood the logic. This was novel to me - while at Xbox I taught myself some SQL so that I could do some stuff I was responsible, but what I didn’t realize is I was so good at learning it because of a boosted processing speed. As a space nerd, this gave me the itch to teach myself Python and R to start scanning images from NASA to help identify planets (before the James Webb telescope launch).<br />
<br />
The tool we used was rule-based to make sure our chat bot Zo didn’t go Nazi like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tay_(chatbot)">Tay</a>, as is the case with most conversational AIs, but the rules weren’t block or allowlists, <em>they were English</em>. It was teaching the machine how to <em>contextually</em> understand English; this opens up the ability to support the intersectionality and range of emotions of the human condition by a machine that’s used to strict rules. We built synonym groups including slang terms, did pen testing to ensure we were controlling the fairness levels appropriately, and I got to experience what it was like working directly on an engineering team…<br />
<br />
Except I wasn’t <em>exactly</em> on the engineering team and got talked to a few times for working on this tool when I was just a social media manager for Zo because it <em>wasn’t part of my responsibilities</em>. The engineer who built that tool will tell you that I understand his tool almost as good as he does - I found bugs that no one had thought to look for, and we made that program so much better over the short time that I was a content analyst before the project was defunded. This role helped me fully understand the need for inclusive and fair technology, something I bring to every role now.<br />
<br />
That team experience was an eye opener which showed me how well I can work on engineering teams and that my performance was significantly better than others when I’m passionate about something. It’s also directly how I landed a role on the Microsoft Edge team after Zo was retired, with my then-manager pushing me towards the community position she realized she wasn’t gonna be a good fit for. Moving from partner to vendor at Microsoft showed me the impact I could make and the speed in which Microsoft moves, but becoming an FTE at the end of 2019 showed me the true firehose of information and workload you get. This is overwhelming for someone who is aware of their weaknesses, significantly more so for someone who is unaware of their diagnoses, strengths, and weaknesses.<br />
<br />
Soon, I’ll post part 2 to talk about my experience on the Microsoft Edge team before and after my diagnosis - something that I feel is really important to differentiate between. Until then!<br />
<br />
-🧜‍♀️🦄</p>]]></content><author><name>the cyborg</name></author><category term="archived" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[AUTHOR NOTE This was originally posted on my WordPress blog, which I have deleted after migrating the blog's posts to this website in November 2025. Differences from the original are minimal and include: rephrasing "neurodiverse" as "neurodivergent" throughout the post, changed a few things to make more grammatical sense, and created more paraphraphs to reduce the wall of text feel. It’s April, which means it’s Autism Acceptance Month! The tech industry believes it to be a space where average people can make a difference in the world, but more often than not these high performing employees are neurodivergent in a neurotypical world. Obligatory note: When you meet someone with autism, you have met one person with autism. We are all unique individuals with a variety of superpowers (some don’t even like that term!), and my experiences are not reflective of the overall neurodivergent community. Are you on the neurodivergent spectrum or think you may be? I’d love to hear your experiences! I’m 100% down to help you navigate this world and how you can be the best you possible. 🥰 Before I begin, I implore you, do not support Autism Speaks, spread the puzzle piece, or speak for autistic people. Make room for us to have our own voices this month - we don’t need your help to be vocal, but we do need your help in elevating our experiences and needs, so take some time this month to make sure you spread the right kind of voices. I’m gonna start this with: Do you realize what all I need to do to ensure my anxiety is under control in this ridiculous world? Unless I’ve told you directly, probably not. Anxiety is often a comorbidity of both autism and ADHD, and it’s quite common to be treated for anxiety when you have either of those. I was diagnosed with bipolar II and severe general anxiety in 2007 and I need 1) an anticonvulsant used as a mood stabilizer to help with my big swings, 2) a traditional mood stabilizer to help sedate me, improve my sleep quality, and keep my anxiety down, 3) an as-needed anti-anxiety medication when things get way fucked, and 4) I constantly use Cognitive Behavior Therapy techniques to bring me back to my center. I’m convinced a large part of this is needed because people value “normal” over “uniqueness” thanks to capitalism, and it’s a huge reason why I would love to just go live on an island tending a community farm far away from tech (Ancient Dreams in a Modern Land is a mood for this). The tech industry is full of neurodivergent people, yet those in charge are in general Boomer age (or have Boomer ideologies), think people who get mental health help are “weak” or “snowflakes”, and often tell their employees to “deal with it”. This leads to excessive stress which leads to over-medication which leads to a lot of people feeling like they are not valued as a human. Now that’s out of the way, this post is part 1 of two about my career experiences before and after my autism diagnosis, focusing on before I was an FTE at Microsoft (part 2 will be about my time on Edge and after my diagnosis). Autism Level 1 was originally called Asperger’s, but we don’t talk about him anymore (bad Nazi doing bad experiments, you should avoid using the term ‘Aspie’ for this reason). AUTHOR'S NOTE, Nov 2025 Past Missy lied, there are actually 3 parts to this series, the third is in drafts as of publishing this. After I was first diagnosed with bipolar II, I learned that working overnights is terrible for bipolar brains. Who’s got two thumbs and was working overnights at Walmart at the time? This bitch. We lived in Colorado (where I was raised) and before this diagnosis I already did a ton of damage to my unfocused career. I exploded at my first job, a bowling alley, because I asked one of my coworkers for a pretzel and cheese from the food counter and he sent back a Slimfast. As I stormed out, I chucked the can at his head (I missed, unfortunately), stopped by the Manager’s office to take off my work shirt and throw it with my badge at the Assistant Manager’s face, then I walked out. I worked at a Denny’s briefly overnights where I was accused of taking meth in the bathroom because I am…uh…too cheery? Wish I was joking about that one. 😑 While I was in trade school to be a mechanic, I worked at a KFC/A&amp;W with a school mate. I hated smelling like chicken all the time so I quit to be a nanny for my old neighbor and a friend of hers. I guess my roommate didn’t like some of that and while I was at my mom’s one extended weekend, that roommate packed all her shit up leaving behind a note and a few ceramic pigs that told me how horrible I was; said pigs were violently introduced to the wall when I read the letter. (To this day I still don’t know what I did to deserve that but her credit got fucked because she didn’t break the lease properly. 😂) I worked in customer service for Microcenter where I kept getting horrible anxiety every day I had to work so I sabotaged that by just…not showing up anymore. All this was within 4 years, 2003-2007, and these are only the job things - I burned a lot more bridges with friends and my husband (then boyfriend) during this time, too. After my bipolar diagnosis, I moved to the day shift at the customer service counter for Walmart. I started medications to control the mood swings, and went through so many before I found the “right” one - I ended up on depakote for a couple years. When we decided we wanted to leave Colorado for the Pacific Northwest in 2008, we moved in with my mother-in-law so that we could save up money for the move across the US. spoiler: we didn’t save anything because we both have ADHD and planning ahead was not a specialty of ours. 😅 But during that time I worked with my mother-in-law as a virtual assistant helping with content creation and editing videos for her clients, and I’m pretty sure I stopped taking my medication and focused solely on CBT. Genuinely can’t recall anymore. In 2010, we decided I needed a “real” job (lol) and my husband saw that a company he used to work for, iBeta, wanted some software testers. He convinced me to apply by telling me, “It’s your favorite thing, pointing out other people’s flaws!” That line actually worked in the interview, and for a year I worked as a software and hardware tester for SMART boards and monitors. To this day, this is my favorite way that explains how I got into tech. I continued to have anxiety issues that would make me call out of work more often than I probably should have; my manager there told me that I would be significantly better at my job if I put more effort into making sure I was around. I didn’t know at the time that I should have been advocating for my anxiety this early in my career, and I wish I did. It’s 2011 now and we finally had enough to move up to Oregon - except we only thought we did and that entire situation was a mess, too. 😬 My first job in Portland, Oregon I lasted only 3 months doing iPhone and iPad phone support. I’m pretty sure that I ruptured a disc because I could not sit for extended periods or in certain ways, but we had no health insurance (because call centers treat their employees like chicken) so I had no way to find out what was really happening. Since I couldn’t take any time off to recover (because how dare call center employees get hurt or sick), I was unfortunately let go. Instead of getting another corporate job, I started building up my own business making jewelry by crowdsourcing funds to buy tools. I taught myself how to solder, learned I could make things in 3D form really well (I always thought I wasn’t artistic), and managed to get a little money out of it. But…me not finding a stable job really hurt us. The cost of that was needing to separate from my husband, give up two of our three cats, and move in with my parents in southern Oregon. My husband still had a job - the one that would eventually change our lives - so he stayed up in Portland by himself working as phone support for Xbox. When I moved back to Portland mid-2012, I ended up getting a job with the husband unit doing phone support for Xbox. The very first phone call I took during training my trainer pulled my husband aside and said, “She sounds like she’s done this her whole life, she’s a natural.” Inside, I was terrified, felt like my voice was wavering, and got an adrenaline rush that gave me a headache and the shakes because of my anxiety. It’s amazing what masking your entire life lets you do. Like I noted in my post about empathy, I was really good at what I did for Xbox, especially once I got confidence in my skills. I was a networking specialist, only one of two women who were on that team. Would you believe that I could easily take my troubleshooting skills from being a trained diesel engine and heavy duty transmission mechanic and fold it into networking? This role taught me how technically-inclined I truly am; I could do in-depth, technical conversations with users and find answers outside of the troubleshooting built into the support tool we used. As support agents, we helped scale up a new call center building in Wilsonville, Oregon and during that transition an opening on the Games for Windows Live team became available. This was a highly desired role within in the call center - they had pretty low call volume and most of the time the answer was “turn off your antivirus”. I scored that seat (the only woman agent on the team with a woman manager) the same time my husband got selected to go up to Redmond and help the Xbox supportability PMs build up the networking section and troubleshooting flows for the original Xbox One. I am still shocked at how well I did at the call center for someone who hates talking to people, but this role is the first one I can see the excessive amount of masking and compensation I was doing to get through things. For example, I got back onto an as-needed anti-anxiety medication so that I wouldn’t sabotage yet another job (lorazepam), found a group of people who were similar to me, and made some new life-long friends. My husband ended up impressing one of the FTEs for Xbox Community Support, and that man (hi, James, if you ever read this!) worked hard to get both of us up to the Seattle area and working on his team. I also mentioned in my empathy post that I was told by my first lead on Xbox, “You talk to problems, not people.” I did not realize that my “learning” empathy and how to engage in text form as a company representative was a form of autistic compensating. I have always been known for not having a filter from my brain to my mouth, not thinking how people would react to a) what I was saying and b) how I was saying it. Tbh, sometimes I still don’t give a shit - sometimes you need that blunt slap in the face because a lot of people won’t do it. I am that friend who will give it to you straight. Shit, I lost track of where I was going with this. Oh, right, how I got unfairly fired from Xbox Community Support due to my lack of filter, directly related to my autism. 🙂‍↕️ I started as a support forums agent, helped launch the Xbox Support handle on Reddit, and moved into a Community Manager role for the Xbox Ambassadors. A beloved staff member of the Ambassadors, I had a rough day and snapped at a community member for being a shithead in Discord. I wasn’t bad about it, he was ranting about something he was upset with, and I said, “Be constructive or be quiet.” I’ll be the first to say I recognize I could have done better there. Very shortly after the exchange this community member left the Discord server. He was well known for this when he would throw a fit, so it wasn’t anything new, and I honestly didn’t even notice because he was still talking to me in private messages. But someone on the team decided that this course of events meant I pushed him out of the community and made it an unsafe space for the rest. Except it wasn’t my interaction with him that made him leave. No one involved with my firing asked the community member what happened, no one talked to other community members like the volunteer moderators who were there, no one talked to me about the situation. About a week after the incident, I get pulled into a room and told that because he left the server after that interaction I was being fired. The member this was centered around tried to petition the team to listen, but they weren’t having it. Mentions of me in the Discord server were removed, a petition on the forums was ignored, my ex-colleagues mostly shunned me. To this day, I (and several others) fully believe that one “bad” interaction after 4 years did not warrant me getting fired. And that’s how I accidentally sabotaged a job I fucking loved by not having a filter thanks to autism, and man if I had known then what I know now things might have gone way different. (Like, probably not getting fired in the first place, for example.) During my time on XCS from 2014-2018, I discovered Halsey (who didn’t at this point, amirite?), learned that she’s openly bipolar and was stoked to see someone like me sing about their experiences. Most of her Badlands album is just a call to my soul, but Gasoline, Castle, and Control are 3 songs that I relate to the most. My cousin was re-diagnosed from bipolar to borderline personality disorder closer to the end of this period, maybe 2017 or 2018. It got me re-evaluating my diagnosis of bipolar as something a little more so I went to a psychologist to get on mood stabilizing medication again and talk more about BPD. I was put on Lamictal then for my bipolar, told that we should focus on the symptoms and not the diagnosis (fine 🙄), and then released once the Lamictal controlled my swings and anxiety. Despite the lack of support for a new diagnosis from this psych, I will forever state that Lamictal saved my life, my relationships, and my career. The role I had after XCS taught me that I love machine learning. As a content analyst for a conversational AI, I learned how to speak to a machine and realized that coding is quite literally simply learning another language - it’s just for machines, and my analytical brain easily understood the logic. This was novel to me - while at Xbox I taught myself some SQL so that I could do some stuff I was responsible, but what I didn’t realize is I was so good at learning it because of a boosted processing speed. As a space nerd, this gave me the itch to teach myself Python and R to start scanning images from NASA to help identify planets (before the James Webb telescope launch). The tool we used was rule-based to make sure our chat bot Zo didn’t go Nazi like Tay, as is the case with most conversational AIs, but the rules weren’t block or allowlists, they were English. It was teaching the machine how to contextually understand English; this opens up the ability to support the intersectionality and range of emotions of the human condition by a machine that’s used to strict rules. We built synonym groups including slang terms, did pen testing to ensure we were controlling the fairness levels appropriately, and I got to experience what it was like working directly on an engineering team… Except I wasn’t exactly on the engineering team and got talked to a few times for working on this tool when I was just a social media manager for Zo because it wasn’t part of my responsibilities. The engineer who built that tool will tell you that I understand his tool almost as good as he does - I found bugs that no one had thought to look for, and we made that program so much better over the short time that I was a content analyst before the project was defunded. This role helped me fully understand the need for inclusive and fair technology, something I bring to every role now. That team experience was an eye opener which showed me how well I can work on engineering teams and that my performance was significantly better than others when I’m passionate about something. It’s also directly how I landed a role on the Microsoft Edge team after Zo was retired, with my then-manager pushing me towards the community position she realized she wasn’t gonna be a good fit for. Moving from partner to vendor at Microsoft showed me the impact I could make and the speed in which Microsoft moves, but becoming an FTE at the end of 2019 showed me the true firehose of information and workload you get. This is overwhelming for someone who is aware of their weaknesses, significantly more so for someone who is unaware of their diagnoses, strengths, and weaknesses. Soon, I’ll post part 2 to talk about my experience on the Microsoft Edge team before and after my diagnosis - something that I feel is really important to differentiate between. Until then! -🧜‍♀️🦄]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The good, the bad, and the uglies of communities</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/archived/good-bad-and-ugly" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The good, the bad, and the uglies of communities" /><published>2023-04-04T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-04-04T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/archived/good%20bad%20and%20ugly</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/archived/good-bad-and-ugly"><![CDATA[<details>
<summary><b>AUTHOR NOTE</b></summary>
<i>This was originally posted on my WordPress blog, which I have deleted after migrating the blog's posts to this website in November 2025. Differences from the original are minimal and include: adding punctuation for flair/clarification of tone, changed formatting on the section headings, adding in paragraphs to reduce the wall of text, changing Twitter to Xitter every chance I get, and adjusted phrasing for a couple lines to be grammatically correct.</i>
</details>
<p><br />
Let’s be real, <b>most</b> communities have something bad about them. There’s no way around it. Personalities clash, moderators can power trip, admins/staff neglecting the space allowing bad seeds to creep up… And it really doesn’t take much for a community to be soured by a bad egg. Since a lot of what I do is ensure that users are heard, I dig hard into community spaces for these companies/products - regardless if I am applying for a product marketing, community management, or product management role.<br />
<br />
If you think you don’t have a community, you’re pretty much <em>wrong</em> - I built a community for a web browser, and I went into that role not thinking the active Insider community would be in the <em>tens of thousands</em>. Your <b>community members are congregating</b> in social spaces, likely complaining about a poor experience with your product or company, <b>breeding negative sentiment</b> - these are the ones you need to start listening to first when you step into a role that includes building a new community. You can <em>really</em> tell a lot about how a company values its community by the state of it, but it’s important to remember that they <em>are</em> looking for someone to listen to these people (<em>at least, according to their job postings</em>). Think of these as flags that may make your job easier or something you need to address to improve brand loyalty and the quality of whatever space you’ll own. Here are the good, the bad, and the ugly (from my experience) that you may find in the communities you need to advocate for in your role.<br />
<br /></p>
<h3 id="the-good">the good</h3>

<p>I want to start with the good things because, I’ll be honest, there is a lot more bad out there than good. This doesn’t mean every community is bad, you just need to weigh both sides as you are introduced to a new community.<br />
<br />
One of the things I <em>love</em> seeing is active volunteer moderators. Having <b>a healthy set of moderators</b> who can handle the <em>volume of posts</em> that come in shows you an understanding of a) how active and engaging the community is and b) the well-being of the volunteers - the people who are giving their free time to help out a company they are not beholden to. Most times, you’re going to step into a role that has an avid fan base who created their own community that you want to become a part of. As long as the community is relatively self-reliant, all you should do is slide in as a representative, not attempt a takeover.<br />
<br />
If you already have <b>a self-sustained, healthy community</b>, all you really need to do is hop in and join the conversation! They don’t want you to come in and disrupt what has worked without you, so <em>don’t</em>. At this point, you get to focus on becoming a valuable part of your new community and building relationships with them. This really <b>removes some of the stress</b> of needing to fully organize a community when you are tasked to be their champion.<br />
<br />
I get downright <em>giddy</em> when I see <b>community members putting together documentation</b> about changes and/or troubleshooting for the product. These people love your stuff - like, <em>LOVE</em> love. They are taking time out of their day to make a support article for you and share it with others so they have the information - FOR FREE. The other side of this coin <em>(and makes this a weird aspect of the bad - we’ll get there</em>) is I start to wonder where the official documentation is… But these people are your big fans, and they want to help others - they’re likely your biggest external advocates, and they need to be shown a ton of appreciation. These are the ones you want to win over immediately when you get into a community, <em>trust me</em>.<br />
<br />
I look for staff or employee activity in these social spaces, and I love seeing <b>staff acting like humans</b> when they engage instead of stiff like PR wrote everything for them. Most tech communities can tell when marketing is giving an approved message and will spot a script-reading support agent from a mile away. It’s not difficult to be a human, so seeing companies trust that their employees won’t make an ass of themselves is a breath of fresh air. This means you get to step into a role that already knows its voice and you don’t need to rework or <em>fight to</em> rework their image.<br />
<br />
I don’t think most people think about this, but how <b>lively off-topic spaces</b> are shows a welcoming community. I view an off-topic space as something you have either already pre-built into your official spaces (like a forum or subreddit you manage, with off-topic sections or tags) or a 3rd-party site that hosts communities allowing for conversations (including Reddit, Xitter, Facebook, Discord… <em>holy shit there’s way too fucking much</em>). Reddit is still kinda viewed as “that platform with the trolls” so communities there are often afterthoughts. My time on Xbox and Edge proved that, <em>yes</em>, there are trolls, but there are <em>way more</em> people willing to help solve whatever issue someone else is having.<br />
<br />
Finding out your <b>share of conversation</b> on any 3rd-party social site is a path to seeing the health of your product’s community. If these sections are talking about more than just your product, you have friendships forming and those people truly value their community. This takes us to…<br />
<br /></p>
<h3 id="the-bad">the bad</h3>

<p>These are things that <em>can</em> be solved but may take some more effort - you’re likely going to run into one or more of these things when you look into a community. This first example is almost too easy to spot and a sign I’m gonna have a rough start because I’ll need to drop a hammer - <b>moderators who appear to be power-tripping</b>.<br />
<br />
Most communities have engagement metrics you can track; whether you hold anyone to them or not is up to you, but they <em>are</em> there. A power-tripping mod can be identified by them marking their comments as an answer, especially <em>before</em> the user comes back. There are exceptions to this - there may be literally one answer (“contact support”), the person is spamming, or the thread is getting locked for violating community guidelines - it shouldn’t be blatantly obvious that they are abusing their status to <em>anyone</em> outside of the community. If <em><b>I</b></em> can spot this, then the community for sure sees it, and they probably don’t respect the moderators or staff who help run things. Why should they? When they see one power-tripping mod they assume that <em>all</em> the mods are power-tripping, and this further’s the community’s perspective that the <em>staff do not care</em>. You have to be willing to have hard conversations coming into situations like this to change that perspective.<br />
<br />
I’ll absolutely do an in-depth dive into community guidelines, Terms of Service/Use, and Privacy Policies for a company. <b>Having community guidelines set up for abuse</b> contributes to power-tripping mods and can silence your community in a way you didn’t intend (<em>or maybe you did? fuck you, if so</em>). I keep an eye out for guidelines that allows moderators to do whatever they want without much oversight, polices how users engage outside of harmful, spamming, and hateful situations, or condescending language in guidelines. These things are harder to adjust because, from my experience, moderators who are used to behaving a certain way without repurcussions will cling to that until they are removed from their position. This is where I take a step back for a bigger picture, review the guidelines that were set up, and see where I need to make appropriate changes. Then I work on re-educating the moderators and/or community on best practices.<br />
<br />
On a related point, <b>staff not believing they need community guidelines</b> is a recipe for creating a toxic community. Your community <em>can</em> self-manage, as I called out in <a href="#the-good">the good</a>, but only if that community has inclusive and diverse volunteer leaders who already created a welcoming set of guidelines. If you decide you want to do <a href="http://nocodeofconduct.com/">No Code of Conduct</a>, I am taking that as a flag that you don’t truly care about your users, their psychological safety, or building a community. Having <b>no</b> guidelines will allow users to create a toxic community and makes room for groups like &lt;<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Timeline_of_events_associated_with_Anonymous">Anonymous</a> to form.<br />
<br />
I may be exaggerating here for effect, but sometimes you need to see <em>the way bad</em> to know what could happen when you decide to not have a way to moderate your community.<br />
<br />
While <b>community members making documentation and training materials</b> can be seen as a good thing, I look into <em>official</em> documentation at that point. Where is it? Is it written for the wrong audience? Should the community-crafted articles be turned into something official? Are these people being recognized by the company for the content they create? Most of these I note and plan on bringing into an interview - at this point I want to find out who I need to work with to improve whatever documentation problems I find.<br />
<br />
Tribal knowledge is something that makes it really hard to support legacy products and having good documentation really goes a long way in product adoption. It takes a lot of product management to organize who knows what internally, confirm the community-created content is accurate, then build up ways to celebrate these community members. It’s 100% worth the work to get through this process to get to celebrating those volunteer efforts, though.<br />
<br />
Now it’s time to dig into…<br />
<br /></p>
<h3 id="the-ugly">the ugly</h3>

<p>Nearly everything related to an ugly community is linked to the employees/staff/the company, and these directly influence if I will put more effort into getting the job. I’m putting <b>employees being condescending to community members</b> as an ugly because this is one of the worst things you need to address coming into a new role. This isn’t just coming in to improve a community, you are also going to have to talk with your new colleagues and train them to <em>properly</em> engage with humans. This is a really odd thing as an autistic woman - training others how to properly engage - because compensating so that I fit in is something I do naturally. I find it weird that others don’t. But it’s one of my superpowers along with <b>empathy</b>, which makes me a great teacher in this case.<br />
<br />
This process is exhausting to me, though, because on top of needing to <a href="https://embrace-autism.com/autism-and-camouflaging/#Masking">mask</a> with a new group of people I <em>also</em> need to teach them how to not be dicks to their users, all without being perceived as a bitch. It’s very intimidating coming to long-standing public faces of a company to let them know, “Hey, maybe you should phrase things this way going forward.” I’m <em>always</em> worried that my colleagues think I am there to police their activity - but I guess I did it well enough in my last role. 😉 If I find during my investigating that it appears to be C-suite people who are doing this, it’s huge red flag that tells me that I shouldn’t move forward with that company - I’m not about to spend my time in that role butting heads with C-suites, it will be a miserable experience for everyone involved. 🫠<br />
<br />
Worse than that is when I discover <b>employees are nowhere to be found</b>! There are a few things I assume when I see this: employees are scared of engaging due to negative sentiment, employees only make a product based on usage data and not the user base, or their PR/Marketing teams have too tight of a hold on how to engage. The “best” part is when <em>all three of these are true</em>. 😵‍💫 I have been told in the past when trying to get an approved message for a product change, “Oh, we show that we’re listening to our users through pRoDucT cHaNgEs, not cOmMuNiCaTiOnS.” That is such <em>utter bullshit</em> that indicates to me a group is scared of engaging with users for fear of pissing them off more.<br />
<br />
Honestly, if you see that you only piss your users off when you try to communicate with them, great job being self-aware! 👏🏻 But also maybe find someone to fix that frame of mind because your community cannot find changes you made if <em>you already pushed them off your product</em> (<em>how is this not common sense?</em>). Becoming best friends with your new PR and Marketing partners when stepping into a role will go a long way in earning their trust that you will engage in a manner that won’t damage the brand or company, but if your main problem here is leadership, you have a bigger bridge to cross to improve communication from the company.<br />
<br />
If <b>your community members are only posting negative</b> things, you have another communication problem. Are you a meme on 3rd-party platforms? Is your product a meme even in official spaces? You are going to have a real uphill battle regaining or even earning the trust of your community at that point. They are used to being neglected by the staff but are still so incredibly passionate that they continue to try to bring these issues up to you. <b>Turning this around</b> involves taking all of their feedback and responding to it, the <b>being open with your community about decisions</b> and why they are made. Along with your superfans and volunteer moderators, you need to listen to the most vocally negative members.<br />
<br />
Creating a product in a social vacuum will alienate certain groups; user research teams don’t ignore the negatives someone brings up during a study, <em>you shouldn’t ignore the same with social listening</em>.<br />
<br />
Finally, the perception that the <b>company is just out for a money grab</b> is something I look for in complaints. It’s on my list of the reasons why I won’t take a new role, and I feel duped by a job listing when I spot these - I am not stepping into a role to <em>sell</em> things, I’m stepping in to improve community sentiment with your product and evangelize your brand. <b>People want empathy</b>, they want <b>to be heard</b>, they want to see <b>meaningful change</b> based on their passion for your product.<br />
<br />
If you decide to implement something that increases costs for your user base, unfairly targets users to encourage them to spend money, and move forward with other business decisions as if your user base isn’t poor, that’s a choice you as a company get to make that <em>I will not support</em>. Inflation is happening worldwide right now, companies are cutting employees <a href="https://news.stanford.edu/2022/12/05/explains-recent-tech-layoffs-worried/">solely because others are</a>, but the big push to consumers is consistently <em>BUY BUY BUY</em>. People are losing their incomes, unable to afford basic necessities, and you are looking at their spending habits instead of their social-economic situation. 😤<br />
<br />
<em>Deep breath, Missy, this wasn’t about your hate of capitalism…</em><br />
<br />
There are nuances that can fall into any of these situations which can tip them to another aspect of this list. I’m sure there are things I missed that I’ve ranted about in the past. If I am looking at your company and the community you want me to help with, this is the stuff that helps me determine if I will push forward with helping you…<br />
<br />
…or if I am just gonna politely step back with my hands up, <em>and run</em>. 💨<br />
<br />
-🧜‍♀️🦄</p>]]></content><author><name>the cyborg</name></author><category term="archived" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[AUTHOR NOTE This was originally posted on my WordPress blog, which I have deleted after migrating the blog's posts to this website in November 2025. Differences from the original are minimal and include: adding punctuation for flair/clarification of tone, changed formatting on the section headings, adding in paragraphs to reduce the wall of text, changing Twitter to Xitter every chance I get, and adjusted phrasing for a couple lines to be grammatically correct. Let’s be real, most communities have something bad about them. There’s no way around it. Personalities clash, moderators can power trip, admins/staff neglecting the space allowing bad seeds to creep up… And it really doesn’t take much for a community to be soured by a bad egg. Since a lot of what I do is ensure that users are heard, I dig hard into community spaces for these companies/products - regardless if I am applying for a product marketing, community management, or product management role. If you think you don’t have a community, you’re pretty much wrong - I built a community for a web browser, and I went into that role not thinking the active Insider community would be in the tens of thousands. Your community members are congregating in social spaces, likely complaining about a poor experience with your product or company, breeding negative sentiment - these are the ones you need to start listening to first when you step into a role that includes building a new community. You can really tell a lot about how a company values its community by the state of it, but it’s important to remember that they are looking for someone to listen to these people (at least, according to their job postings). Think of these as flags that may make your job easier or something you need to address to improve brand loyalty and the quality of whatever space you’ll own. Here are the good, the bad, and the ugly (from my experience) that you may find in the communities you need to advocate for in your role. the good]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The art of empathy</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/archived/art-of-empathy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The art of empathy" /><published>2023-03-27T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-03-27T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/archived/art%20of%20empathy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/archived/art-of-empathy"><![CDATA[<details>
<summary><b>AUTHOR NOTE</b></summary>
<i>This was originally posted on my WordPress blog, which I have deleted after migrating the blog's posts to this website in November 2025. Differences from the original are minimal and include: changing Twitter to Xitter every chance I get, adding links to screenshots of referenced Xitter posts because my inactive profile is locked down, adding in paragraphs to reduce the wall of text, and adjusting text formatting.</i>
</details>
<p><br />
Recently I posted on Xitter some <b><a href="https://imgur.com/a/CQ9JuVg">red flags in communities</a></b> while job hunting. Some may see this as dangerous to publicly talk about while job hunting, but I really don’t. That ended up spiraling into this blog, a space where I can effectively talk about my experiences as a community manager, product marketing manager, and customer advocate. I’ve been around a few different communities over my career; voluntarily running communities with my friends as a teenager and young adult as an admin for role playing forums to being a Guild Master of a few World of Warcraft Guilds, moving professionally to brands like Xbox and Microsoft Edge. Between those two roles, I championed for a community that used a conversational AI, something I know most people can’t say they’ve done.<br />
<br />
I was part of the first-round layoffs at Microsoft in January 2023. While doing research into companies for potential roles I interview for I’ve been digging into a variety of communities to find some glaring issues that they <em>definitely</em> need help with. It’s important information to share: how to understand what you are getting into as a community manager or product marketing manager. I guess you can now see how this rolled into <b><a href="https://imgur.com/a/oNO3qq6">people convincing me to start a blog</a></b>.<br />
<br />
When thinking of the post titles that Dona challenged me to provide, one thing I knew I could talk about ad nauseum was <b>active listening in customer service</b>. Absolutely no disrespect meant towards the actual employees in customer service roles - I worked my way up through call centers and truly understand the hell you go through and what is required of you (sometimes ridiculously). Companies in general do not value customer service, it’s often the first considered in a budget cut and outsourced to reduce those costs further.<br />
<br />
Not a lot of customer service agents truly empathize with their customers for a wide variety of reasons, and it frustrates <em>the fuck</em> out of literally everyone. You’ve had that bad customer service experience, <em>I know you have</em>. The empathy aspect in the initial goal of this post wasn’t obvious to me at first. It wasn’t until <a href="https://imgur.com/a/lZlQwtj">new Bing suggested a few potential titles</a> I could use that it clicked - you can actively listen but still sound like you are reading from a script, it’s the <b>empathy</b> and <b>understanding the person on the other side</b> that is often missing.<br />
<br /></p>
<details>
<summary><b>AUTHOR'S NOTE, Nov 2025</b></summary>
<i>el oh el fuck Windows, Bing, and everything that comes with their "AI".</i>
</details>
<p><br />
My first lead on Xbox Community Support said, “I can teach you the tech, but I can’t teach you to care.” That’s both true and not true in my experience; there’s some people you can teach but <em>definitely</em> not everyone (<em>think of the planet we would have if we could teach everyone how to care</em>). But I’ll never forget that line and think of it when I train people on talking to customers, working to show the human on the other side of the screen when engaging. Sure, you may not <em>really</em> care about them; I definitely can’t say I’ve loved everyone I’ve ever interacted with as a community lead. But you sure as hell can <b>use active listening</b> to <b>show empathy</b> and relate to them a little. This goes a long way in a heated conversation, which can be the case in customer service situations, and it’s <b><em>surprisingly easy</em></b>.<br />
<br />
I held a <b>100% CSAT</b> score <b>over two years</b> of doing phone support for Microsoft, and I distinctly recall one of my coworkers saying, “You have that calm mom voice on the phone.” That was bizarre to me considering I actively hate talking to other people.<br />
<br />
<em>No offense to other people</em>, it’s the masking I hate, being an autistic social butterfly in a “neurotypical” tech world will be a post I do in the future. (Edit: <a href="/archived/being-audhd-part-1">Part 1</a> and <a href="/archived/being-audhd-part-2">Part 2</a> are both up now!)<br />
<br />
It’s true, though, I had a way to calm customers with my voice and the ability to not only recognize their technical level but speak to them at it without being condescending. There’s a really fine line when walking someone through something and not being condescending while doing it, it’s easy to go over that line if you aren’t actively looking for it. Now, typing the same kind of stuff I was performing through speech on the phones wasn’t the same at first; that first lead also told me, “You talk to problems, not people.” Again, <em>autism</em>, but I had no idea at the time so we’ll glaze over that to focus on the fact that I was able to learn how to use active listening and empathy together using text.<br />
<br />
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Active_listening">Active listening</a> is an underutilized skill, imho. People say they can do it, but rarely do they practice it. The amount of emails I’ve received from <em>colleagues</em> who clearly did not read what I wrote… 🙄 “<em>Per. My. Last. Email.</em>” but ~P R O F E S S I O N A L~. It <b>can</b> be taught. One aspect of having empathy while engaging with users is having <b>a solid understanding of a product</b>. It’s easy when you’re an engineer or PM for a product, you basically built or are actively building the thing! Excellent, one thing down.<br />
<br />
Now, look at what that user said in their ticket/social post/email/<em>wtf ever else</em>. <b>Can you tell what they mean</b>? If <em>any</em> part of you says no, you need to focus on asking for clarification instead of assuming <em>anything</em>. “Hey, I want to make sure I fully understand here. When you say <b>x</b>, do you mean <b>y</b>? Or do you mean <b>z</b>? Or maybe I am way off and you mean something else completely. 😅 I’d love to help out further but want to ensure we’re on the same page.” Yes, <em>use emojis</em> if it’s the right tone, that’s just how we all talk these days - <b>be a human first</b>.<br />
<br />
Sometimes you already know what they mean, like when they say bookmarks instead of favorites. Other clues are in the experience they describe, sometimes you can see the missing piece that the user doesn’t know is missing and causing their issue. <b>Product knowledge helps active listening</b> so well when engaging with users on any platform, and one thing a lot of companies don’t do is <b>properly train their support agents</b> on the product. Most are <em>still</em> trained to click through a script and there are now virtual agents (read: chat bots) that do half of it before you talk to a human anyway. Support agents are so conditioned to click through a script that they will ask users who send in complaints explaining the steps they have already followed to go through the <em>exact. same. troubleshooting</em>. You’ve probably had that experience, too. This whole process <b>feels incredibly condescending</b> and <b>doesn’t value the individual</b> who just came to you asking for your further help.<br />
<br />
I bet <b>product knowledge</b> wasn’t what you thought I would say first before empathy can properly kick in, didja? I’m gonna blow your mind even further.<br />
<br />
Empathy in customer service also requires <b>following up with your users</b>. I’m sure you’ve contacted customer service for a company needing to talk to someone new <em>yet again</em> for an escalated issue instead of getting that call or email you were promised. <em>Just look at my account, the reference number should be attached! 😭</em> Following up with people using active listening and product knowledge has been <b><a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/MicrosoftEdge/comments/i7cazk/comment/g18hnfs/">the biggest delighter customers talked about</a></b> over my career.<br />
<br />
Most call centers work in a way that does not allow employees to follow up, which is just honestly tragic; call center employees are often treated like chickens earning their feed for the eggs they push out. As a networking specialist for Xbox phone support, I was luckily given the flexibility to follow up with users I had active tickets for. Working as one of 4 - 6 Xbox support agents for the forums (depending on the point in our team’s existence), I owned my own follow ups, handing them to my teammates if I went on vacation to ensure my commitment to the user was held.<br />
<br />
While working for the Microsoft Edge team, I would set honest expectations with users in not only my one-on-one technical troubleshooting with them but in the Edge Insider communications so the community knew when we would be back. “The team is going dark for the next couple weeks as we observe a summer holiday! Expect only Canary to get updates, and we will be back in a few weeks with what’s new in Dev.” <em>or</em> “I am gonna be out on vacation next week, so I’ll be back the following Monday with an update for you. Please tag me if you don’t hear from me then!” There’s just something about honoring your commitments that <b>builds solid brand loyalty</b>.<br />
<br />
The last thing I will say is required while offering customer service or community building is just <b>consciously practicing <a href="https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/empathy">empathy</a></b> itself! Put yourself in their shoes. In fact, my entire post should have shown you that you <em>have</em> been in their shoes. When I respond to a frustrated user, I call out that I read their pain points and express them back to them, show that I feel for their situation and that I just want to help instead of attempt to sell the product. I <b>respond like a human</b>, not a PR-bot, and focus on the user themselves.<br />
<br />
Like I said, it’s surprisingly easy to show empathy while building a community, whether you are helping them learn something new or troubleshooting something that may be broken. None of this requires you to be friends with the person, but if you <b>understand where they are coming from</b>, <b>respect their technical level</b> (or lack thereof), and <b>have a solid understanding of what you are talking about</b>, you can take your community’s experience with your team and push it a bar above the rest.<br />
<br />
-🧜‍♀️🦄</p>]]></content><author><name>the cyborg</name></author><category term="archived" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[AUTHOR NOTE This was originally posted on my WordPress blog, which I have deleted after migrating the blog's posts to this website in November 2025. Differences from the original are minimal and include: changing Twitter to Xitter every chance I get, adding links to screenshots of referenced Xitter posts because my inactive profile is locked down, adding in paragraphs to reduce the wall of text, and adjusting text formatting. Recently I posted on Xitter some red flags in communities while job hunting. Some may see this as dangerous to publicly talk about while job hunting, but I really don’t. That ended up spiraling into this blog, a space where I can effectively talk about my experiences as a community manager, product marketing manager, and customer advocate. I’ve been around a few different communities over my career; voluntarily running communities with my friends as a teenager and young adult as an admin for role playing forums to being a Guild Master of a few World of Warcraft Guilds, moving professionally to brands like Xbox and Microsoft Edge. Between those two roles, I championed for a community that used a conversational AI, something I know most people can’t say they’ve done. I was part of the first-round layoffs at Microsoft in January 2023. While doing research into companies for potential roles I interview for I’ve been digging into a variety of communities to find some glaring issues that they definitely need help with. It’s important information to share: how to understand what you are getting into as a community manager or product marketing manager. I guess you can now see how this rolled into people convincing me to start a blog. When thinking of the post titles that Dona challenged me to provide, one thing I knew I could talk about ad nauseum was active listening in customer service. Absolutely no disrespect meant towards the actual employees in customer service roles - I worked my way up through call centers and truly understand the hell you go through and what is required of you (sometimes ridiculously). Companies in general do not value customer service, it’s often the first considered in a budget cut and outsourced to reduce those costs further. Not a lot of customer service agents truly empathize with their customers for a wide variety of reasons, and it frustrates the fuck out of literally everyone. You’ve had that bad customer service experience, I know you have. The empathy aspect in the initial goal of this post wasn’t obvious to me at first. It wasn’t until new Bing suggested a few potential titles I could use that it clicked - you can actively listen but still sound like you are reading from a script, it’s the empathy and understanding the person on the other side that is often missing. AUTHOR'S NOTE, Nov 2025 el oh el fuck Windows, Bing, and everything that comes with their "AI". My first lead on Xbox Community Support said, “I can teach you the tech, but I can’t teach you to care.” That’s both true and not true in my experience; there’s some people you can teach but definitely not everyone (think of the planet we would have if we could teach everyone how to care). But I’ll never forget that line and think of it when I train people on talking to customers, working to show the human on the other side of the screen when engaging. Sure, you may not really care about them; I definitely can’t say I’ve loved everyone I’ve ever interacted with as a community lead. But you sure as hell can use active listening to show empathy and relate to them a little. This goes a long way in a heated conversation, which can be the case in customer service situations, and it’s surprisingly easy. I held a 100% CSAT score over two years of doing phone support for Microsoft, and I distinctly recall one of my coworkers saying, “You have that calm mom voice on the phone.” That was bizarre to me considering I actively hate talking to other people. No offense to other people, it’s the masking I hate, being an autistic social butterfly in a “neurotypical” tech world will be a post I do in the future. (Edit: Part 1 and Part 2 are both up now!) It’s true, though, I had a way to calm customers with my voice and the ability to not only recognize their technical level but speak to them at it without being condescending. There’s a really fine line when walking someone through something and not being condescending while doing it, it’s easy to go over that line if you aren’t actively looking for it. Now, typing the same kind of stuff I was performing through speech on the phones wasn’t the same at first; that first lead also told me, “You talk to problems, not people.” Again, autism, but I had no idea at the time so we’ll glaze over that to focus on the fact that I was able to learn how to use active listening and empathy together using text. Active listening is an underutilized skill, imho. People say they can do it, but rarely do they practice it. The amount of emails I’ve received from colleagues who clearly did not read what I wrote… 🙄 “Per. My. Last. Email.” but ~P R O F E S S I O N A L~. It can be taught. One aspect of having empathy while engaging with users is having a solid understanding of a product. It’s easy when you’re an engineer or PM for a product, you basically built or are actively building the thing! Excellent, one thing down. Now, look at what that user said in their ticket/social post/email/wtf ever else. Can you tell what they mean? If any part of you says no, you need to focus on asking for clarification instead of assuming anything. “Hey, I want to make sure I fully understand here. When you say x, do you mean y? Or do you mean z? Or maybe I am way off and you mean something else completely. 😅 I’d love to help out further but want to ensure we’re on the same page.” Yes, use emojis if it’s the right tone, that’s just how we all talk these days - be a human first. Sometimes you already know what they mean, like when they say bookmarks instead of favorites. Other clues are in the experience they describe, sometimes you can see the missing piece that the user doesn’t know is missing and causing their issue. Product knowledge helps active listening so well when engaging with users on any platform, and one thing a lot of companies don’t do is properly train their support agents on the product. Most are still trained to click through a script and there are now virtual agents (read: chat bots) that do half of it before you talk to a human anyway. Support agents are so conditioned to click through a script that they will ask users who send in complaints explaining the steps they have already followed to go through the exact. same. troubleshooting. You’ve probably had that experience, too. This whole process feels incredibly condescending and doesn’t value the individual who just came to you asking for your further help. I bet product knowledge wasn’t what you thought I would say first before empathy can properly kick in, didja? I’m gonna blow your mind even further. Empathy in customer service also requires following up with your users. I’m sure you’ve contacted customer service for a company needing to talk to someone new yet again for an escalated issue instead of getting that call or email you were promised. Just look at my account, the reference number should be attached! 😭 Following up with people using active listening and product knowledge has been the biggest delighter customers talked about over my career. Most call centers work in a way that does not allow employees to follow up, which is just honestly tragic; call center employees are often treated like chickens earning their feed for the eggs they push out. As a networking specialist for Xbox phone support, I was luckily given the flexibility to follow up with users I had active tickets for. Working as one of 4 - 6 Xbox support agents for the forums (depending on the point in our team’s existence), I owned my own follow ups, handing them to my teammates if I went on vacation to ensure my commitment to the user was held. While working for the Microsoft Edge team, I would set honest expectations with users in not only my one-on-one technical troubleshooting with them but in the Edge Insider communications so the community knew when we would be back. “The team is going dark for the next couple weeks as we observe a summer holiday! Expect only Canary to get updates, and we will be back in a few weeks with what’s new in Dev.” or “I am gonna be out on vacation next week, so I’ll be back the following Monday with an update for you. Please tag me if you don’t hear from me then!” There’s just something about honoring your commitments that builds solid brand loyalty. The last thing I will say is required while offering customer service or community building is just consciously practicing empathy itself! Put yourself in their shoes. In fact, my entire post should have shown you that you have been in their shoes. When I respond to a frustrated user, I call out that I read their pain points and express them back to them, show that I feel for their situation and that I just want to help instead of attempt to sell the product. I respond like a human, not a PR-bot, and focus on the user themselves. Like I said, it’s surprisingly easy to show empathy while building a community, whether you are helping them learn something new or troubleshooting something that may be broken. None of this requires you to be friends with the person, but if you understand where they are coming from, respect their technical level (or lack thereof), and have a solid understanding of what you are talking about, you can take your community’s experience with your team and push it a bar above the rest. -🧜‍♀️🦄]]></summary></entry></feed>